See them tumbling down
Pledging their love
to the ground
راوی: در غرب دور عزیزی بود.
NARRATOR: Way out West
there was this fella.
عزیزی که می‌خوام داستانشو براتون بگم
Fella I wanna tell you about.
عزیزی به اسم
جف لبوفسکی
Fella by the name
of Jeff Lebowski.
اقلن این اسمی بود که پدر مادر عزیزش براش گذاشتن
£east that was the handle
that his loving parents
gave him.
ولی خودش خیلی فاز اسمشو نداشت
But he never had
much use for it himself.
این لبوفسکی،
به خودش می‌گفت «دوود»
This Lebowski,
he called himself the Dude.
حالا دود
Now Dude,
تو شهر ما کسی اسم خودشو همچی چیزی نمی‌ذاره
that's a name no one would
self-apply where I come from.
ولی حالا می‌بینم خیلی چیزا راجع به دود بود
که زیاد برای من مفهوم نبود
But then there was a lot about
the Dude that didn't make
a whole lot of sense to me,
خیلی چیزام راجع‌به جایی که زندگی می‌کرد
and a lot about
where he lived likewise.
Drifting along with
the tumbling tumbleweeds
ولی شایدم
NARRATOR: But then again,
واسه همین بود که فاز اونجا رو انقد شدید داشتم
maybe that's why
I found the place
so darned interesting.
I know when night has gone
That a new world's
born at dawn
به لوس آنگلس می‌گن شهر فرشته‌ها
NARRATOR:
They call Los Angeles
the City of Angels.
بنظرم خیلی هم اینطوریا نیست
I didn't find it to be that,
exactly.
ولی قبول دارم یه سری آدمای خوبی اونجا هستن
But I'll allow there are
some nice folks there.
البته بگم من لندنم ندیدم
Course, I can't say
I seen London,
فرانسه هم نرفتم
and I never been to France,
بقول یارو گفتنی تاحالا ملکه رو تو لباس زیرش ندیدم..
and I ain't never seen no
queen in her damned undies,
as the fella says.
ولی یه چی بگم،
But I'll tell you what,
بعد دیدن لس آنجلس و همین این قصه که می‌خوام شرحشو بدم
after seeing Los Angeles
and this here story
I'm about to unfold,
نمی‌دونم، شاید بشه گفت یه چیزایی دیدم
well, I guess
I've seen something
به همون اندازه داغون که میشه تو اون شهرا دید
every bit as stupefying
as you can see in any of
those other places,
و تو ادبیات انگلیسی هم
and in English, too.
پس می‌تونم با یه لبخند رو صورتم بمیرم
So I can die with
a smile on my face
بی اینکه حس کنم خدای مهربان گولم زده
without feeling like
the good Lord gypped me.
حالا این داستانی که می‌خوام بگم
Now, this here story
I'm about to unfold
اوایل دهه‌ی ۹۰ اتفاق افتاد
took place back
in the early '9·s,
درست اولای درگیریمون با صدام و عراقیا
just about the time
of our conflict with
Saddam and the lraqis.
فقط می‌گم که، گاهی اوقات یکی هست
I only mention it 'cause
sometimes there's a man...
نمی‌گم قهرمان
I won't say a hero.
اصلن ینی چی قهرمان؟
'Cause what's a hero?
ولی گاهی وقتا یکی هست
But sometimes there's a man...
اینجام دارم درمورد دود حرف می‌زنم
And I'm talking about
the Dude here.
بعضی وقتا یکی هست
Sometimes there's a man...
چی‌بگم، آدم مناسب زمان و مکان خودشه
Well, he's the man
for his time and place.
درست جا می‌گیره همونجا
He fits right in there.
که اونم دود توی لوس آنجلسه
And that's the Dude
in Los Angeles.
با اینکه تن لش هم هست
And even if he is a lazy man,
که دود قطعا هم همینطور بود
and the Dude was
most certainly that,
احتمالا تن لش ترین در منطقه لوس آنجلس
quite possibly the laziest
in Los Angeles county,
که اونو در صدر تن لشای جهان قرار می‌ده
which would place him
high in the running
for laziest worldwide.
ولی بعضی وقتا یکی هست
But sometimes there's a man...
بعضی وقتا یکی هست
Sometimes there's a man...
ای‌بابا
رشته افکارم از هم گسسته شد
Well, I lost my train
of thought here.
ولی..
But...
جهنم. قدر کافی معرفی‌ش کردم
Hell, I done introduced him
enough.
بوش پدر در تلوزیون:  جهت انجام یک حرکت جمعی با همه‌ی اونها
BUSH ON TV: ...with them all
for a collective action.
این قابل تحمل نیست
This will not stand.
این قابل تحمل نیست، این حمله علیه.. کویت
This will not stand,
this aggression
against Kuwait.
Here on the range I belong
Drifting along
With the tumbling
Tumbleweeds
(YELLING)
(DUDE EXCLAIMING)
(SPLUTTERING)
(GASPS)
پولا کجاست لبوفسکی؟
Where's the money,
Lebowski?
پولا رو بده بیاد لبوفسکی
I want that money,
Lebowski.
بانی گفت تو می‌دیش
Bunny says you're
good for it.
پولا کجان لبوفسکی؟
Where's the money,
Lebowski?
پولا کجان لبوفسکی؟
Where's the money,
Lebowski?
پولای لعنتی کجان آشغااال
Where's the fucking money,
shithead?
(PANTING)
اون پایین ماییناس
بذا یه نگا دیگه بندازم..
It's down there somewhere.
Let me take another look.
با دم شیر بازی نکن.
Don't fuck with us.
زنت بدهکار جکی تریهورنه
Your wife owes money
to Jackie Treehorn,
ینی تو بدهکار جکی تریهورنی
that means you owe money
to Jackie Treehorn.
با مفتخورا از قدیم همین کارو کردن، لبوفسکی
Ever thus to deadbeats,
Lebowski.
ای بابا ن..
No, don't do...
نه روی فرش.. حاجی..
آقا: دیدی؟
Not on the rug, man.
MAN: See?
دیدی چه اتفاقی میفته لبوفسکی؟
دیدی چه اتفاقی میفته؟
See what happens, Lebowski?
You see what happens?
کسی به من نمی‌گه لبوفسکی.
شماها اشتباه گرفتین.
Nobody calls me Lebowski.
You got the wrong guy.
من دوودم حاجی.
I'm the Dude, man.
اسمت لبوفسکیه،
لبوفسکی
Your name's Lebowski,
Lebowski.
زنتم بانیه.
Your wife is Bunny.
(STAMMERS)
زنم؟ بانی؟
My wife? Bunny?
حلقه ازدواج می‌بینی رو دست من؟
Do you see a wedding ring
on my finger?
اینجا می‌گه من یه ازدواج لعنتی کردم؟
Does this place look like
I'm fucking married?
در توالت بالاس بابا!
The toilet seat's up, man!
این چه کوفتیه؟
What the fuck is this?
واضحه که شما گلف‌باز نیستی
Obviously you're
not a golfer.
وو؟
هان.
Woo?
Yeah.
این یارو قرار نبود میلیونر باشه؟
Isn't this guy supposed
to be a millionaire?
وو: زرشک
WOO: Fuck.
آره. نظرت چیه؟
Yeah. What do you think?
یارو عین یه بازنده‌ی لعنتیه..
He looks like
a fucking loser.
هی، اقلن تو جاش کارامو می‌کنم..
Hey, at least I'm housebroken.
وقت تلف کن لعنتی..
Fucking time-waster.
دمت گرم،
آشغال.
Thanks a lot,
asshole.
(DOOR SLAMS)
(THE MAN lN ME PLAYING)
La-la-la, la-la-la, la-la-la
La-la-la, la, la, la, la
La-la-la, la, la, la-la la-la
£a, la, la-la
La-la-la
La-la-la, la-la-la
La-la, la-la
مرد درون من
The man in me will do
هر کاری بگی می‌کنه
Nearly any task
در ازای مزدش هم
And as for compensation
یه توقع کوچیک داره
There's little he would ask
که زنی مثل تو داشته باشه
Take a woman like you
که اونو برسونه
To get through
به مرد درون من
To the man in me
ابرهای طوفانی قرش می‌کنن
Storm clouds are raging
طرفای خونه‌ی من
All around my door
با خودم فکر می‌کنم که
I think to myself
شاید دیگه تحملش رو نداشته باشم
I might not take it anymore
یه زنی مثل خودت رو بیار
Take a woman like your kind
که مرد درون من رو پیدا کنه
To find the man in me
ولی هی..
But, oh
عجب حس عجیبیه
What a wonderful feeling
که بدونم تو نزدیکی
Just to know that you are near
دل من رو می‌لرزونه
Sets my heart a-reeling
از نک پام بگیر
From my toes
تا گوش‌هام
Up to my ears
مرد درون من گاهی وقتا قایم می‌شه
The man in me will
hide sometimes
تا کسی اونو نبینه
To keep from being seen
ولی این فقط به این خاطر هست که
But that's just because
he doesn't want
اون نمی‌خواد مثل یه روبات بشه
To turn into some machine
یه زنی مثل خودت رو انتخاب کن
Take a woman like you
که برسه
To get through
به مرد درون من
To the man in me
ووپس
(WHOOPS)
؟؟؟؟؟؟؟؟
علامت بزن دود.
I'm throwing rocks tonight.
Mark it, Dude.
والتر: دارم می‌گم بهت
این فرش قیمتی بود.
این ئه...
WALTER: I'm telling you,
this was a valued rug.
This was a...
آره حاجی. واقعا یه انسجامی به اتاق می‌داد.
Yeah, man. It really
tied the room together.
این یه شئ قیمتی..
This was
a valued...
چی به اتاق انسجام می‌داد دود؟
قالیم
What tied the room
together, Dude?
My rug.
داشتی به داستان دود گوش می‌دادی تو، دانی؟
Were you listening
to the Dude's story,
Donny?
چی؟
والتر.
What?
Walter.
داشتی داستان دودو گوش می‌دادی آیا؟
داشتم توپ می‌نداختم
Were you listening
to the Dude's story?
I was bowling.
پس هیچ ایده‌ای از بحث نداری، دانی.
So you have no frame of
reference here, Donny.
عین بچه‌ای می‌مونی که یهو اومده از وسط فیلم
می‌خواد بدونه..
You're like a child who
wanders into the middle of
a movie and wants to know...
والتر.. منظورت چیه رفیق؟
هیچ دلیلی نداره،
منظورم اینه دود
Walter, what's
the point, man?
There's no reason,
here's my point, Dude.
هیچ دلیلی نیست
که چرا این دوتا
There's no fucking reason
why these two...
آره والتر.
منظورت چیه؟
Yeah, Walter,
what's your point?
والتر.. بابا..
Walter, what is the...
ببین ما می‌دونیم تقصیر کی بوده الان
Look, we all know
who is at fault here.
پس اصن راجع‌به چی حرف می‌زنی؟
هان؟
What the fuck are
you talking about?
Huh?
نه تو راجع به چی حرف می‌زنی؟
من ن..
No, what the fuck
are you... I'm not...
ما داریم راجع به تهاجم مهارنشده صحبت می‌کنیم، دوود.
We're talking about
unchecked aggression
here, Dude.
چی می‌گه این؟
قالیم.
What the fuck is
he talking about?
My rug.
ولش کن دانی. نداری فازو
Forget it, Donny!
You're out of
your element!
والتر. این چشم‌بادومی که فرشمو کثیف کرد
Walter, the Chinaman
who peed on my rug,
نمی‌تونم برم بهش قبض جریمه بدم که!!
I can't go
give him a bill!
پس اصلن راجع به چی حرف می‌زنی؟
So what the fuck
are you talking about?
تو راجع به چی حرف می‌زنی؟
What the fuck are
you talking about?
چشم‌بادومیه اصلن موضوع بحث نیست الان، دود!
The Chinaman is not
the issue here, Dude!
من راجع به کشیدن خط فرضی توی شن صحبت می‌کنم، دود.
I'm talking about
drawing a line in
the sand, Dude.
روی این خط، شما ن..
Across this line
you do not...
درضمن، دوود، «چشم بادومی» لغت پسندیده‌ای نیست.
Also, Dude, "Chinaman"
is not the preferred
nomenclature.
آسیایی-آمریکایی، خواهشا..
Asian-American,
please.
والتر این یارو اونی نیست که راه‌آهن‌های اینجارو ساخته
این یارو..
Walter, this isn't a guy
who built the railroads
here. This is a guy...
چی می‌گ..؟
What the fuck
are you...
والتر این یارو ریده رو فرش من.
ریده رو فرش دوود.
Walter, he peed
on my rug!
He peed on
the Dude's rug.
دانی، هیچی نمی‌دونی حرف نزن.
Donny, you're out
of your element.
دوود، ما اصلن راجع به چشم بادومیه صحبت نمی‌کنیم
Dude, the Chinaman
is not the issue here.
پس، کی..
جف لبوفسکی
So, who...
Jeff Lebowski.
اونیکی جف لبوفسکی.
اون میلیونره..
The other Jeffrey Lebowski.
The millionaire.
ایول بابا.. این شد یه چیزی..
این شد یه چیزی..
That's fucking
interesting, man.
That's fucking interesting.
بعلاوه، این ثروتش رو هم داره،
و مشخصا منابعش رو
Plus, he has the
wealth, obviously,
and the resources,
پس هیچ دلیلی نیست،
هیچ دلیل احمقانه‌ای نیست
so that there's no reason,
there's no fucking reason
که زنش بره بیرون و تو کل شهر قرض بالا بیاره
why his wife should
go out and owe money
all over town,
بعد هم اونا هم بیان برینن رو فرش قشنگ تو
and then they come
and they pee on your
fucking rug!
بد می‌گم؟
نه.
Am I wrong?
No.
بد می‌گم؟
آره. ولی..
Am I wrong?
Yeah, but...
والتر: خیل خب.
WALTER: Okay then.
(WALTER CLEARS THROAT)
اون فرش واقعا به اتاق انسجام می‌بخشید، مگه نه؟
That rug really tied
the room together,
did it not?
آهر بابا
این یارو هم شاشید روش
Fucking A.
And this guy peed on it.
دانی. لطفا.
Donny, please.
می‌دونی. این همون آشغالیه که
You know, this is
the fucking guy...
اصن من میتونم این لبوفسکیه رو گیرش بیارم
I could find this
fucking Lebowski guy.
اسمش لبوفسکیه؟
این که اسم توئه دوود!
His name is Lebowski?
That's your name, Dude.
این یارو باید خسارت منو برا فرش بده.
This is the guy who
should compensate me
for the fucking rug.
زنش می‌ره بیرون و تو شهر بدهی میاره بالا،
اینام میان میشاشن به فرش من؟
His wife goes out and
owes money all over town,
and they pee on my rug?
اینا بیان بشاشن به فرش خوشگل تو؟
They pee on
your fucking rug?
شاشیدن به فرش قشنگ من.
همینه. دوود.
Peed on my fucking rug.
That's right, Dude.
ریدن به فرش خوشگل تو.
They peed on
your fucking rug.
این هم اتاق مطالعه‌ست.
This is the study.
همونطور که می‌بینید، انواع جوایز و افتخارات..
As you can see, the various
commendations, awards...
»جفری لبوفسکی»
ارجاعات، درجات و غیره..
"Jeffrey Lebowski."
...citations, honorary
degrees, et cetera.
خیلی جالبه
اوه. خواهش می‌کنم مشاهده‌شون کنید
Very impressive.
Oh, please feel free
to inspect them.
اوه. نه. خیلی الان..
اوه. تقاضا می‌کنم، تقاضا می‌کنم.
Oh. No, I'm not really...
Oh, please. Please.
این کلید شهر پاسادیناست
That is the key to
the city of Pasadena,
که آقای لبوفسکی دو سال پیش برای قدردانی از
تلاش‌هایی که برای شهر..
which Mr. Lebowski received
two years ago in recognition
of his various civic...
اوه. این جایزه شخص موفق تجارت از اتاق بازرگانی لس آنجلس‌ه
Oh! That's the Los Angeles
Chamber of Commerce
Business Achiever Award,
که هر سال،
البته نه الزاما هر سال داده می‌شه.
which is given...
Oh, not necessarily
given every year.
ئه. این..
Hey, is this...
فقط وقتی یک فرد لایق پیدا بشه.
Given only when there's
a worthy somebody...
این اونه با نانسی؟
Is this him with Nancy?
بله. همینطوره. این آقای لبوفسکی هستن
با بانوی اول. درسته.
Yes, indeed,
that is Mr. Lebowski
with the first lady, yes.
این عکس زمانی گرفته شد که خانم ریگان
It was taken
when Mrs. Reagan...
لبوفسکی این سمت چپیه‌س؟
That's Lebowski
on the left there?
بله. آقای لبفسکی سمت چپ
پس ینی..
Of course. Mr. Lebowski,
on the left...
So he's a...
می‌گم ینی معلول و ایناست؟
You know, a handicapped
kind of guy?
بله. آقای لبوفسکی ناتوان هستن. درسته.
Mr. Lebowski is
disabled, yes.
این عکس زمانی گرفته شد که خانم ریگان بانوی اول کشور بودن.
This picture was taken
when Mrs. Reagan was
first lady of the nation.
بله. بله.
Yes, yes.
نه کالیفرنیا.
عکس خوبیه.
Not of California.
Good shot.
اتفاقا با رئیس‌جمهور هم بطور خصوصی ملاقات کردن
In fact, he met privately
with the President,
ولی متاسفانه فرصت کافی برای گرفتن عکس نبود.
though, unfortunately,
there wasn't enough time
for a photo opportunity.
اوه. نانسی‌م خوبه.
بله. زن فوق‌العاده‌ی هستن.
Oh, Nancy's pretty good.
Oh, wonderful woman.
ما خیلی خوشحال هستیم که..
اینا..
We were very happy to...
These are...
اوه. این‌ها بنوعی فرزندان آقای لبوفسکی هستن.
Oh, those are
Mr. Lebowski's
children, so to speak.
مادرهاشون یکی نیست که. نه؟
Different mothers, huh?
نه. اونا..
اون از لحاظ نژادی خیلی قوی و ایناست؟
No, they're not...
Racially, he's
pretty cool?
(LAUGHING)
اونا واقعا بچه‌های ایشون نیستن.
They're not literally
his children.
اونا لبوفسکی‌های کوچیک‌های موفق شهر هستن
They're the Little Lebowski
Urban Achievers,
کودکان پر استعداد شهر که امکانات لازم..
inner city children
of promise, but without
the necessary means for...
امکانات لازم برای تحصیلات عالی رو در اختیار ندارن
Necessary means for
a higher education,
برای همینه که آقای لبوفسکی تعهد کردن که همشون رو به کالج بفرستن.
so Mr. Lebowski is
committed to sending
all of them to college.
عذر می‌خوام.
او. عجب.
Excuse me.
Oh, geez.
ممنون. متشکرم.
Thank you. Thank you.
عجب. یکی دیگه نمی‌خواد ازینا بنظرت؟
یکی.. آهان.
Far out. Think he's got
room for one more?
One... Oh.
شما انگار کالج نرفتین.
You never went to college.
لطفا دست نزنید.
چرا اتفاقا. چرا. نه. رفتم.
Please, don't touch that.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
No, I did,
ولی می‌دونی، بیشتر وقتم رو
but, you know,
I spent most of my time
صرف بسط‌نیشنی توی ساختمونای اداری مختلف و
occupying various
administration buildings,
کشیدن چوب تایلندی**** و
smoking a lot
of Thai stick,
بولینگ و .... ***‌بودم.
(LAUGHING)
breaking into the ROTC
and bowling.
راستشو بخوای برندت خیلی بخشاشو اصلن یادم‌م نمیاد.
Tell you the truth, Brandt,
I don't remember most of it.
(SCOFFS)
(DOOR OPENS)
خیل‌خب قربون.
شما لبوفسکی هستی.
منم لبوفسکی‌م
Okay, sir.
You're a Lebowski,
I'm a Lebowski.
خیلی هم خوب.
That's terrific.
ولی من خیلی پرمشغله هستم
و حدسم اینه که شما هم همینطور هستید.
But I am very busy,
as I imagine you are.
چه‌کار براتون می‌تونم بکنم، قربان؟
What can I do for you, sir?
خب ببینید،
یه فرشی هست که من دارم.
Well, sir,
it's this rug I have.
که واقعا یه انسجامی به اتاق می‌بخشید.
It really tied
the room together.
شما پشت تلفن به برندت گفتید. اون به من گفت.
You told Brandt
on the phone.
He told me.
نقش من چی هست؟
Where do I fit in?
خب ببینید. دنبال شما می‌گشتن این دوتا.
Well, they were looking
for you, these two guys.
می‌دونید. اونا..
دوباره می‌گم
You know, they...
I'll say it again.
شما پشت تلفن به برندت گفتید. اونم به من گفت.
You told Brandt on the phone.
He told me.
می‌دونم چه اتفاقی افتاده.
البته؛ البته.
I know what happened.
Yes, yes.
پس درجریانید قصدشون این بود رو قالی شما خرابکاری کنن؟
Oh, so you know that
they were trying to
piss on your rug.
من قالی شما رو بولی کردم؟
Did I urinate on your rug?
منظورتون اینه که شما شخصا اومدید و قالی منو کثیف کردید؟
You mean, did you personally
come and pee on my rug?
سلام! انگلیسی بلدید صحبت کنید قربان؟
Hello! Do you speak
English, sir?
%Parla usted ingl·s?
دوباره می‌پرسم.
من قالی شما رو بولی کردم؟
I'll ask you again.
Did I urinate on your rug?
نه. گفتم که.
وو فرشم رو کثیف کرد.
No. Like I said,
Woo peed on my rug.
فقط یه چیزی رو می‌خوام بفهمم قربان.
I just want to
understand this, sir.
هروقت به محظر یه فرشی تو این شهر بزرگ توهین می‌شه،
Every time a rug
is micturated upon
in this fair city,
من باید به صاحابش خسارت پرداخت کنم؟
I have to compensate
the person?
ببین، رفیق..
من نمی‌خوام خدای نکرده پول زور از کسی بگیرم.
Come on, man.
I'm not trying to
scam anybody here.
می‌دونی، فقط می‌خوا..
You know, I'm just...
شما فقط دنبال یه کمکی هستی مثل هر..
You're just looking for
a handout like every other...
آیا شما شاغل هستید آقای لبوفسکی؟
Are you employed,
Mr. Lebowski?
صب کن. بذار یه چیزی رو تشریح کنم براتون.
Wait. Let me explain
something to you.
من آقای لبوفسکی نیستم.
I am not Mr. Lebowski.
شما آقای لبوفسکی هستین.
من دوود هستم.
You're Mr. Lebowski.
I'm the Dude.
پس منو به همین اسم هم صدا می‌زنید.
متوجهید؟
So that's what you call me.
You know?
یا اون، یا دودمقام
That or His Dudeness,
یا دوودی، مثلا،
or Duder or, you know,
یا عالیجناب دودورینو، اگه خیلی به ایجاز و اختصار معتقد نیستی.
El Duderino, if you're not
into the whole brevity thing.
آیا شما شاغل هستید، جناب؟
Are you employed, sir?
شاغل؟
Employed?
(CHUCKLES)
شما با این لباس نمی‌رید دنبال کار بگردید که، می‌رید؟
در روز کاری؟
You don't go out looking for
a job dressed like that,
do you? On a weekday?
آیا این..؟
Is this a...
چن‌شنبه‌س امروز؟
ببینید، من کار می‌کنم، قربان.
What day is this?
Well, I do work, sir.
پس اگه با این قضیه مشکلی ندارین..
چرا خیلی هم مشکلی دارم.
دود با این قضیه مشکل داره.
So, if you don't mind...
No, I do mind.
The Dude minds.
این تحمل نمی‌شه. حواستون هست؟
This will not stand, you know.
این حمله تحمل نمی‌شه. آقا.
This aggression
will not stand, man.
منظورم اینه که
زن شما بدهکاره..
I mean,
your wife owes money...
زن من اصلا موضوع بحث نیست الان!
My wife is not
the issue here!
امیدوارم روزی زن من یاد بگیره در حدود اختیاراتش زندگی کنه
I hope that someday
my wife will learn to
live on her allowance,
که بسیار هم گسترده‌ست.
which is ample.
ولی اگه نکنه، مشکل اونه
نه من
But if she does not,
that is her problem,
not mine,
همونطوری که قالی مشکل شماست.
just as the rug
is your problem.
همونطوری که هر مفت‌خوری، مسئول سرنوشت زندگی خودش هست
Just as every bum's
lot in life is his
own responsibility,
فارغ ازینکه چه کسی رو مقصر بدونه
regardless of who
he chooses to blame.
من کسی رو مسبب دست رفتن پاهام ندونستم.
I didn't blame anyone
for the loss of my legs.
یک چینی اونا رو تو کره از من گرفتشون.
Some Chinaman took them
from me in Korea.
ولی من رفتم و در هر صورت به موفقیت رسیدم.
But I went out
and achieved anyway.
(CHUCKLES)
من نمی‌تونم مشکلات شما رو حل کنم جناب.
فقط خود شما می‌تونین.
I cannot solve
your problems, sir.
Only you can.
خب. به کفشم.
اوه، به کفشت..
Well, fuck it.
Oh, fuck it.
آره. جواب شما همینه.
جواب شما به همه‌چیز همینه.
Yes, that's your answer.
That's your answer
to everything.
بدین رو پیشونیتون بنویسن!
Tattoo it on your forehead!
انقلابتون تموم شده، آقای لبوفسکی!
Your revolution is over,
Mr. Lebowski!
تسلیت می‌گم! مفت‌خورا باختن!
Condolences! The bums lost!
توصیه من به شما اینه که
همون کاری رو بکنید که والدینتون کردن!
My advice to you is to do
what your parents did!
برید سر کااار، قربان!
Get a job, sir!
مفت‌خورا همیشه خاسرن!
The bums will
always lose!
می‌شنوی لبوفسکی؟
Do you hear me,
Lebowski?
مفت‌خورا همیشه خااسرن!
The bums will
always lose.
جلسه چطور پیش رفت آقای لبوفسکی؟
How was your meeting,
Mr. Lebowski
خووب
Okay.
رئیس گفت هر فرشی دوست داشتی وردار ببر.
The old man told me to take
any rug in the house.
خب. امیدوارم بهتون خوش بگذره.
Well, enjoy.
و اینکه دوباره شما رو ببینیم دوود.
And perhaps we'll see you
again sometime, Dude.
آره. حتما.
Yeah, sure.
می‌دونی، آگه یه وقت تو محله بودم،
If I'm in the neighborhood,
you know,
(SALSA MUSIC PLAYING ON RADIO)
و می‌خواستم برم دستشویی.
and I need to use the john.
فوتشون کن.
هان؟
Blow on them.
Huh?
یالا. فوت کن.
Go ahead. Blow.
می‌خوای من انگشتاتو فوت کنم؟
You want me to blow
on your toes?
آره!
Uh-huh.
نمی‌تونم خودم اونجارو فوت کنم.
I can't blow that far.
مطمئنی اون شاکی نمی‌شه؟
Are you sure he won't mind?
بانی: اوولی هیچی براش مهم نیست.
اون نیهیلیست‌ه.
BUNNY: Uli doesn't
care about anything.
He's a nihilist.
آخی. باید حوصله‌سربر باشه.
Oh, that must be exhausting.
فوت نمی‌کنیا!
You're not blowing.
مهمون ما باید کم‌کم بره،
خانم لبوفسکی
Our guest has to
be getting along,
Mrs. Lebowski.
اوه!
Oh!
شما بانی هستی!
You're Bunny.
۱۰۰۰ دلار می‌گیرم تختتو مرتب می‌کنم.
I'll suck your cock
for $1 ,000.
یک زن فوق‌العاده!
Wonderful woman.
ما خیلی مفتخریم بهش.
خیلی روح آزادی داره.
We're all very fond of her.
Very free-spirited.
ولی برندت نمی‌تونه نگاه کنه.
وگرنه باید ۱۰۰ دلار بده.
Brandt can't watch though,
or he has to pay $100.
عاالیه.
That's marvelous.
من یه تک پا می‌رم ای‌تی‌ام گیر بیارم..
I'm just gonna go
find a cash machine.
(WHOOPS)
I'm slamming them tonight!
You guys are dead
in the water.
والتر: ایول! باریکلا، داانی!
WALTER: All right!
Way to go, Donny!
(DOG WHINING)
اگه اراده کنی‌، رویا نیست
"lf you will it,
it is no dream."
۲۰ دقیقه دیر کردی حاجی.
این چیه؟
Fucking 20 minutes late, man.
What the fuck is that?
تئودور هرزل.
هان؟
Theodore Herzl.
Huh?
منطقه اسرائیل.
اگر اراده کنی، دوود، رویا نیست.
State of lsrael.
If you will it, Dude,
it is no dream.
چی داری می‌گی واسه خودت آخه؟
What the fuck are you
talking about, man?
این که دستت گرفتی. چیچیه تو این که دستت گرفتی؟
هان؟
The carrier. What's in
the fucking carrier?
Huh?
اوه! سگ سینتیا
فک کنم پومرنیان ه
Oh! Cynthia's dog.
Think it's a Pomeranian.
نمی‌تونم خونه تنهاش بذارم.
مبلارو می‌جوهه
Can't leave him home alone
or he eats the furniture.
نگهش داشتم تا سینتیا و مارتی آکرمن از هاوایی بیان.
I'm watching it
while Cynthia and Marty
Ackerman are in Hawaii.
یه پومرنیان رو ورداشتی آوردی بولینگ؟
You brought a fucking
Pomeranian bowling?
ینی چی آوردمش بولینگ؟
What do you mean,
brought it bowling?
نه براش کفش گرفتم. نه براش آبجو می‌گیرم.
I didn't rent it shoes.
I'm not buying it
a fucking beer.
نوبت تو رم قرار نیست بگیره دوود.
He's not taking your
fucking turn, Dude.
حاجی اگه زن سابق من ازم می‌خواست سگ کوفتی‌شُ نگه دارم
Man, if my fucking ex-wife
asked me to take care of
her fucking dog
تا خودشو دوست پسرش برن هانولولو
while she and her boyfriend
went to Honolulu,
بهش می‌گفتم برو درتو بذا
چرا نمی‌گیره اینو؟
I'd tell her to
go fuck herself.
Why can't she board it?
اول از همه دود،
تو زن سابق نداری.
First of all, Dude,
you don't have an ex.
دوما، این سگ نمایشی‌ه با برگه و فلان.
Secondly, this is
a fucking show dog
with fucking papers.
نمی‌تونی بگیرش.
ناراحت می‌شه.
موهاش می‌ریزه.
You can't board it.
It gets upset.
lts hair falls out.
والتر..
سگ کوفتی برگه و کوفت و زهرمار داره.
Walter...
Fucking dog has
fucking papers.
پا روی خط!
هاه؟
Over the line!
Huh?
شرمنده اسموکی. پات رو خط بود. این خطاست.
I'm sorry, Smokey.
You were over the line.
That's a foul.
ریدی بابا. ۸ بزن دوود.
Bullshit. Mark it eight, Dude.
شرمنده. صفر بزن.
بعدی
Excuse me. Mark it zero.
Next frame.
زر نزن والتر. ۸ بزن دوود.
Bullshit, Walter.
Mark it eight, Dude.
اسموکی اینجا ویتنام نیست.
اینجا بولینگه.
قانون حکم‌فرماست.
Smokey, this is not Nam.
This is bowling.
There are rules.
هی والتر. بیخیال رفیق.
اسموکیه بابا.
Hey, Walter, come on.
Hey, man, it's Smokey.
ببین یکم انگشتش از خط رد شد.
حواست هست؟
So his toe slipped over
a little, you know.
این فقط یه بازی‌ه بابا.
این بازی لیگه.
It's just a game, man.
This is a league game.
که مشخص می‌کنه کی میره مرحله بعد.
This determines who enters
the next round robin.
غلط می‌گم؟
اسموکی: آره ولی من ن..
Am I wrong?
SMOKEY: Yeah, but I wasn't...
غلط می‌گم؟
آره ولی من پام رو خط نبود.
Am I wrong?
Yeah, but I wasn't over.
ماژیکو بده دود. من ۸ ُمی‌زنم.
Give me the marker, Dude.
I'm marking an eight.
اسموکی دوست من.
Smokey, my friend,
تو داری وارد یک عالم درد و رنجش می‌شی.
والتر، بابا!
you're entering
a world of pain.
Walter, man.
این امتیازو ۸ وارد می‌کنی و وارد یک دنیا درد و رنجش می‌شی.
You mark that frame an
eight, you're entering
a world of pain.
وارد نمی‌کنم.
یک دنیا درد و رنجش
I'm not...
A world of pain.
ببین دود، این هم‌تیمی توئه.
Look, Dude,
this is your partner.
نکنه دنیا وارونه شده یا که بهم ریخته؟
Has the whole world
gone crazy?
این فقط منم که قانون و اینارو به بیضه‌ش حساب می‌کنه؟
Am I the only one
around here who gives
a shit about the rules?
صفر رو بزن!
Mark it zero!
(DOG BARKING)
بابا دارن زنگ می‌زنن پلیس دیگه!
تفنگو بذار کنار..
They're calling the cops, man.
Put the piece away.
صفرو بزن!!
دوود: والتر تفنگو بذار کناار!
Mark it zero!
DUDE: Walter,
put the piece away.
والتر.
فک کردی باهات شوخی دارم؟
Walter.
You think I'm fucking
around here?
صفرو بزن!
Mark it zero!
خیل خب! صفر ه لعنتی!
All right. It's fucking zero.
خوشحال شدی لعنت دیوونه؟
You happy,
you crazy fuck?
این بازی لیگه، اسموکی
It's a league game,
Smokey.
(DOG BARKING)
نمی‌تونی اینطوری کنی حاجی.
You can't do that, man.
اینا، می‌دونی، مثل منن. صلح طلبن.
These guys, you know,
they're like me,
they're pacifists.
اسموکی خودش معترض باوجدانی بود.
Smokey was a
conscientious objector.
ببین دود. من خودم در یه مقطعی درگیر صلح‌طلبی و این قضایا شدم.
You know, Dude,
I myself dabbled in
pacifism at one point.
که تو ویتنام هم نبود البته.
Not in Nam, of course.
ببین تازه اون جدای از این قضیه مشکلات عاطفی هم داره، عزیز.
And you know he's got
emotional problems, man.
منظورت ورای صلح‌طلبیه؟
You mean, beyond pacifism?
اون شکننده‌س.
خیلی شکننده‌س.
He's fragile.
He's very fragile.
من که نمی‌دونستم.
I did not know that.
ببین دیگه الان
این قضیه آب زیر پله.
Well, it's all water
under the bridge.
تازه، ما هم که به مرحله بعد صعود کردیم
And we do enter
the next round robin.
آیا من در اشتباهم؟
نه والتر در اشتباه نیستی.
Am I wrong?
No, you're not wrong.
در اشتباهم؟
در اشتباه نیستی، والتر.
Am I wrong?
You're not wrong, Walter.
تو فقط یه آشغالی.
You're just an asshole.
(SIREN WAILING)
خیل خب پس.
Okay then.
بازی با کونتانا و ا٬برایان برا هفته‌ی بعد.
Play Quintana and
O'Brien next week.
بردنشون باید عین آب  ِخوردن باشه.
They should be pushovers.
ببین رفیق. می‌تونی یکم فقط..
Man, would you just...
فقط شل کن یکم لطفا.
Just take it easy, man.
ببین، این جواب تو به همه‌چیه دوود.
You know, that's your answer
for everything, Dude.
بذار به یه نکته‌ای رو تبیین کنم.
صلح‌طلبی این ن..
Let me point out something.
Pacifism is not...
یه نگا به اوضاع فعلیمون با این شترباز تو عراق بنداز.
Look at our current
situation with that
camel fucker in lraq.
صلح‌طلبی چیزی نیست که بخوای پشتش پناه بگیری.
Pacifism is not something
to hide behind.
فقط یکم آروم باش لطفا!
Just take it easy, man.
من کاملا آرومم دوود.
I'm perfectly calm, Dude.
آره، می‌بینم. با این تفنگ کوفتیت؟
از تو آرومترم!
Yeah, waving the
fucking gun around?
Calmer than you are.
ممکنه یکم آروم باشی!؟
Will you just take it easy?
از تو آرومترم..
Calmer than you are.
(ANSWERING MACHINE BEEPS)
دوود، اسموکی‌م.
SMOKEY ON MACHINE:
Dude, this is Smokey.
ببین نمی‌خوام خیلی کلید کنم رو این قضیه.
Look, I don't wanna be
a hard-on about this,
و حواسمم هست که تقصیر تو نبود.
and I know
it wasn't your fault,
ولی فک کردم منصفانه‌س بهت بگم
but I just thought
it was fair to tell you
که من و گیلبرت می‌خوایم این قضیه رو به لیگ گزارش کنیم.
that Gilbert and I will be
submitting this to the league
و ازشون بخوایم که این راند رو درنظر نگیرن.
and asking them
to set aside the round.
نمی‌دونم، مثلا نتیجه رو بنفع ما اعلام کنن.
I don't know,
maybe forfeit it to us.
پس، همونطور که گفتم، یه هشداری دادم.
So, like I say, just thought,
you know, fair warning.
به والتر بگو.
Tell Walter.
شرمنده.
I'm sorry.
(BEEPS)
آقای لبوفسکی،
برندت‌م، از..
Mr. Lebowski,
this is Brandt at...
خب از دفتر آقای لبوفسکی.
Well, at Mr. Lebowski's
office.
لطفا هر وقت براتون مقدور بود با ما تماس بگیرین.
Please call us
as soon as it's convenient.
(BEEPS)
آقای لبوفسکی،
من مل زلنیکر هستم
Mr. Lebowski,
this is Mel Zelnicker
از لیگ بولینگ کالیفورنیای جنوبی.
of the Southern Cal
Bowling League.
من یک گزارش غیر رسمی دریافت کردم که یکی از اعضای تیم شما
والتر سوبچاک نامی
I just got an informal report
that a member of your team,
a Walter Sobchak,
در خلال بازی لیگ
سلاح گرم کشیده.
drew a firearm
during league play.
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
البته اگر این صحت داشته باشه
If this is true, of course,
چند بند از مواد قانون لیگ رو نقض می‌کنه
it contravenes a number of
the league's bylaws
همچنین ماده ۲۷ از قانون لیگ
and also article 27
of the league...
دوود.
چطوری مارتی؟
Dude.
Hey, Marty.
دوود، بالاخره گرفتم
Dude, I finally got...
این مکانی رو که می‌خواستم گرفتم.
I got the venue I wanted.
این رقص پنج‌تاییم رو قراره اجرا کنم. می‌دونی، سایکلم‌رو..
I'm performing
my dance quintet,
you know, my cycle,
سه‌شنبه شب توی  خیابون فانتین سالن کرین جکسن.
at Crane Jackson's
Fountain Street Theater
on Tuesday night.
و، خب، خوشحال می‌شم اگه بیای و نظرت رو بهم انتقال بدی.
And, well, I'd love it if
you came and gave me notes.
حتما میام، رفیق.
I'll be there, man.
دوود. فردا هم ۱۰‌م ه ها..
Dude, tomorrow's
already the tenth.
عجب.
Far out.
آهان. هان. باشه. حله.
Oh. Oh, all right. Okay.
فقط اجاره رو از زیر در خونه‌م رد کن.
Just slip the rent
under my door.
تخلف جدی هست و موقعیت شما در جدول رو تحت تاثیر قرار می‌ده
ZELNICKER ON MACHINE:
...serious infraction
and examine your standing.
متشکرم.
Thank you.
(BEEPS)
آقای لبوفسکی. برندتم دوباره.
Mr. Lebowski, Brandt again.
لطفا به محظ اینکه رسیدید تماس بگیرید تا من لیموزین رو بفرستم.
Please do call us
as soon as you get in
and I'll send the limo.
امیدوارم بخاطر قضیه فرش نباشه که تلفن رو جواب نمی‌دین.
I hope you're not avoiding
this call because of the rug,
که مطمئن باشید اصلا مشکلی نیست.
which I assure you
is not a problem.
ما به کمکتون احتیاج داریم و..
We need your help, and...
خیلی دوست داریم شما رو ببینیم.
خیلی متشکرم. برندت بودم.
Well, we would very
much like to see you.
Thank you. It's Brandt.
(BEEPS)
We've had some
terrible news.
Mr. Lebowski's in seclusion
in the west wing.
Mr. Lebowski.
جالبه..
Funny.
من می‌تونم نگاه کنم به یک عمر موفقیت
I can look back on
a life of achievement,
چالش‌های گذر کرده
challenges met,
رقبایی که شکست داده شدن،
competitors bested,
موانعی که ازشون گذر شد.
obstacles overcome.
من بیشتر از اکثر انسان‌ها به موفقیت رسیدم
I've accomplished
more than most men
بدون بهره مندی از نعمت پاهام.
and without
the use of my legs.
مرد بودن به چه چیزی هست، آقای لبوفسکی؟
What makes a man,
Mr. Lebowski?
دوود.
هان؟
Dude.
Huh?
نمی‌دونم قربون..
Oh, I don't know, sir.
آیا به این نیست که برای انجام کار درست آماده باشی
Is it being prepared
to do the right thing,
فارغ از هزینه‌ها
whatever the cost?
این اون چیزی نیست که به مرد بودن معنی می‌ده؟
Isn't that what
makes a man?
البته. این و یه جفت بیضه.
Sure, that and
a pair of testicles.
دارین مزاح می‌کنین.
You're joking,
ولی احتمالا درست هم می‌گین.
but perhaps you're right.
اشکالی داره من یه جی بکشم؟
You mind if I do a Jay?
بانی.
Bunny.
ببخشید؟
Excuse me?
بانی لبوفسکی
Bunny Lebowski.
اون نور زندگی منه.
She is the light of my life.
از اشک‌های من متعجب شدید آقا؟
Are you surprised
at my tears, sir?
اوه. آره.
Oh, fucking A.
مردان پرصلابت هم گریه می‌کنند..
Strong men also cry.
(CLEARS THROAT)
لبوفسکی: من این فکس رو امروز دریافت کردم.
LEBOWSKl: I received
this fax this morning.
همونطور که می‌بینید، یه نامه‌ی خونبها‌ست.
As you can see,
it is a ransom note.
دود: بانی پیش ما بیده.
DUDE: "We have Bunny."
از طرف کسانی که قادر به کسب موقیت در بازی منصفانه نبودند.
Written by men who were
unable to achieve on a
level field of play.
یک ملیون دلار جمع وکنید..
"Gather $1 million..."
یاقیان.
هاا ای توو دسته‌های بی علامت و غیر پشت سر هم.
Cowards!
"...in unmarked,
nonconsecutive 2·s."
سست عنصران!
هاا ایی منتظر دستورالعمل هم وباشید
Weaklings!
"Await instructions."
مفت‌خوران!
بامزه بازی هم در نویارید.
Bums!
"No funny stuff."
ضدحال.
هاه؟
Bummer.
Huh?
این خیلی ضدحاله حاجی..
این.. این ضد حاله..
This is a bummer, man.
That's... That's a bummer.
برندت در جریان ریزه‌کاری‌ها قرارتون می‌ده.
Brandt will fill you in
on the details.
Mr. Lebowski is prepared
to make a generous offer
to you to act as courier
once we get instructions
for the money.
Why me, man?
He believes the culprits
might be the very people
who soiled your rug
and you are in a unique
position to confirm or
disconfirm that suspicion.
He thinks the carpet pissers
did this?
Well, Dude,
we just don't know.
(LATINO MUSIC PLAYING)
Welcome to the
Hotel California
Such a lovely place
کنتانای لعنتی
Fucking Quintana.
انتر ترکونده‌ها، عن.
That creep can roll, man.
آره. ولی آدم پستی‌ه دوود.
آره.
Yeah, but he's
a pervert, Dude.
Yeah.
نه. اون معارض جنسیه. پرونده هم داره
No, he's a sex offender
with a record.
۶ ماه تو زندان چینو بوده چون خودشو به یه بچه ۸ ساله نشون داده.
He did six months in Chino
for exposing himself
to an eight-year-old.
(PINS FALLING)
والتر: وقتی رفت هالی‌وود، مجبور شد خونه به خونه بره
WALTER: When he moved
to Hollywood, he had
to go door-to-door
به همه بگه شاهدبازه.
to tell everyone
he was a pederast.
دانی: شاهدباز چیه والتر؟
ببند دهنتو دانی.
DONNY: What's a
pederast, Walter?
Shut the fuck up, Donny.
خب. چقد دادن بهت؟
So, how much
did he give you?
۲۰ هزارتا بابا!.
و البته، فرش رو هم دیگه می‌تونم نگه دارم.
20 grand, man.
And, of course,
I still get to keep the rug.
فقط واسه اینکه پولو رد و بدل کنی؟
آره.
Just for making
a hand-off?
Yeah.
(BEEPS)
به دوود هم این بیپر رو دادن.
They gave Dude a beeper.
که هروقت اینا زنگ زدن..
اگه وسط بازی بود چی؟
So whenever
these guys call...
What if it's
during a game?
اوه، بهشون گفتن اگه بین بازی لیگ بود..
Oh, I told them
if it was during
league play...
چی بین بازی لیگ بود؟
What's during
league play?
زندگی به خواست تو قطع و وصل نمی‌شه
Life does not
stop and start
at your convenience,
انتر رغت آور.
you miserable
piece of shit.
حساب کردم..
والتر چشه دوود؟
I figure...
What's wrong with
Walter, Dude?
حساب کردم پول بادآورده‌س دیگه.
خطر نداره که.
I figure
it's easy money, you know.
It's all pretty harmless.
احتمالا خود زنه خودش رو ربوده.
She probably
kidnapped herself.
منظورت چیه دوود؟
قالی‌برینا این کارو نکردن.
What do you mean, Dude?
Rug-peers did not do this.
با دقت به قضیه نگاه کن. یه همسر لوبت برای پول، زن این یارو می‌شه
Look at it. A young
trophy wife marries
this guy for his money.
بعد حساب می‌کنه می‌بینه یارو بقدر کافی پول نداده بهش. حواست هست.
She figures he isn't
giving her enough,
you know.
به کل شهر قرض بالا میاره.
She owes money
all over town.
ای هرزه‌ی لعنتی!
That fucking bitch!
اصن همش ظاهرسازی‌ه رفیق..
It's all a goddamn
fake, man.
مثل حرفیه که لنین زد
It's like Lenin said,
ببین سود رو چه کسی می‌بره و .. حواست هست.
you look for the person
who will benefit
and, you know...
من والروس‌م؟
حواست هست. می‌فهمی که..
I Am the Walrus?
You know, you'll...
می‌گیری چی می‌خوام بگم؟
من والروس‌م.
You know what
I'm trying to say.
I Am the Walrus.
اون جنده‌ی لعنتی!
آره!
That fucking bitch!
Oh, yeah!
من والروس‌م.
این..
I Am the Walrus.
That's...
دانی ببند دهنتو.
Shut the fuck up,
Donny!
وی. ای. لینین. ولادیمیر ایلویچ اویانو
V.l. Lenin, Vladimir
llyich Ulyanov!
در مورد چی حرف می‌زنه این؟
What the fuck is
he talking about?
دقیقا همین شده برا اینا..
Fucking exactly what
happened to those...
والتر: این قضیه حالم رو بهم می‌زنه.
WALTER: That makes me
fucking sick!
دوود: به تو چه ربطی داره والتر؟
اون خرپولای عوضی.
DUDE: Well, what do
you care, Walter?
Those rich fucks.
کل این داستان.
This whole fucking thing.
من ننشستم که جون دادن رفیقام رو ببینم،  درحالیکه صورتشون قرق در لجن بود
I did not watch my buddies
die face down in the muck
که این فاحشه‌ی عوضی
so that this
fucking strumpet,
این بدکاره‌ی لعنتی بتونه اینور اونور برقصه
this fucking whore,
could waltz around...
من اصلن ربطش رو با ویتنام درک نمی‌کنم، رقیق.
I don't see any connection
with Vietnam, man.
ببین ربطش بوضوح مشخصه، دود.
Well, there isn't a
literal connection,
Dude.
نه والتر. بپذیر. هیچ ربطی نداره.
No, Walter, face it,
there isn't any connection.
چرت می‌گی.
هرطور می‌خوای فک کن.
Your roll.
Have it your way.
چرت می‌گی.
منظورم اینه
Your roll.
But my point is...
منظورم اینه
کوینتانا: آماده‌ی گاییده شدن هستید دوستان؟
My point is...
QUINTANA: Are you ready
to be fucked, man?
شنیدم تا نیمه‌نهایی سینه‌خیز اومدید.
I see you rolled your way
into the semis.
Dios mfo, man.
لیام و من، قرارو درتونو بذاریم.
Liam and me,
we're gonna fuck you up.
آره. ببین این صرفا تصور توئه دوست من.
Yeah? Well, you know,
that's just like
your opinion, man.
بذا یه چی به تو بگم احمق جان
Let me tell you
something, pendejo.
اگه بخوای یکی ازین عن‌بازیاتو برا ما در بیاره
You pull any of your
crazy shit with us,
یه تفنگی چیزی بکشی
you flash a piece out
on the lanes,
اول ازت می‌گیرمش و می‌ذارمش در سوراخ اونجات
I'll take it away from you
and stick it up your ass
بعدم ماشه رو می‌کشم تا بگه
کلیک.
and pull the fucking trigger
till it goes click.
جیزز!
Jesus.
همینه که گقتی
You said it, man.
هیچکی سربسر جیزز نمی‌ذاره.
Nobody fucks with the Jesus.
بچه ۸ ساله‌ها، دوود.
Eight-year-olds, Dude.
(PINS FALLING)
(MEN EYCLAIMING)
(THE MAN lN ME PLAYING)
La-la-la, la-la-la, la-la-la
La-la-la, la, la, la, la
La-la, la-la
La-la-la
La-la-la, la-la-la
La-la, la-la
The man in me will do
Nearly any task
And as for compensation
There's little he would ask
(SCREAMING)
Take a woman like you
To get through
To the man in me
Storm clouds are raging
All around my door
I think to myself
I might not take it anymore
Take a woman like your kind
To find the man in me
But, oh
(BEEPER BEEPING)
What a wonderful feeling
Just to know
That you are near
(GROANS)
Sets my heart a-reeling
(MUTTERING)
From my toes
Up to my ears
The man in me
will hide sometimes
BRANDT: They called
about ·0 minutes ago.
They want you
to take the money,
drive north on the 405.
They will call you
on the portable phone
with instructions
in about 40 minutes.
One person only.
They were very clear on that,
or I'd go with you.
One person only.
What happened
to yourjaw?
Oh, nothing, man.
Here's the money.
And the phone.
Please, Dude, follow
whatever instructions
they give.
All right.
Her life is in your hands.
Man, don't say that.
Mr. Lebowski
asked me to repeat that,
her life is in your hands.
Oh, shit, man.
Her life is in
your hands, Dude.
Report back to us
as soon as it's done.
Where the fuck
are you going, man?
Take the ringer,
I'll drive.
The what?
The ringer.
The ringer, Dude.
DUDE: What the...
Have they called yet?
What the hell is this?
My dirty undies, Dude.
The laundry. The whites.
Walter, I'm sure there's
a reason you brought
your dirty undies, man.
That's right, Dude.
The weight.
The ringer cannot look empty.
Walter, what the fuck
are you thinking, man?
You're right, Dude.
I got to thinking.
I got to thinking,
why should we settle for
a measly fucking 20 grand...
We? What the fuck, "we"?
You said you just wanted
to come along.
My point, Dude,
is why should we
settle for 20 grand
when we can keep
the entire million?
Am I wrong?
Yes, you're wrong. This
isn't a fucking game, man.
Oh, but it is a game.
You said so yourself.
She kidnapped herself.
I said I thought...
(PHONE RINGING)
Dude, here.
MAN: (WITH GERMAN ACCENT)
Who is this?
Dude. The bagman, man.
Where do you want us to go?
Us?
Shit!
Yeah, you know,
me and the driver.
I'm not handling the money,
driving the car and talking
on the phone all by my...
Shut the fuck up!
Dude, are you
fucking this up?
Who is that?
That is the driver.
I told you...
(DIAL TONE HUMS)
Oh, shit!
What the fuck's going on?
Walter...
What the fuck is going on?
He hung up, man.
You fucked it up.
You fucked it up!
Her life was in
our hands, man.
Easy, Dude.
We're screwed now.
We don't get shit.
They're gonna kill her.
We're fucked, Walter.
Nothing is fucked, Dude.
Come on.
You're being very un-Dude.
They'll call back.
Look, she kidnapped...
(PHONE RINGING)
You see? Nothing's
fucked here, Dude.
Nothing is fucked.
They're a bunch of
fucking amateurs.
Walter, will you just
shut the fuck up?
Don't say peep while
I'm doing business here, man.
Okay, Dude.
Have it your way.
But they're amateurs.
Fuck.
Dude.
MAN: Okay, we proceed
but only if there
is no funny stuff.
Yeah, yeah.
So no funny sturt Okay?
Just tell me where the fuck
you want us to go.
That was the sign, man.
So, all we gotta do
is get her back.
No one's in a position
to complain.
We keep the baksheesh.
Yeah, terrific, Walter.
But you haven't told me
how we're gonna get her
back. Where is she?
That's the simple part, Dude.
We make the hand-off,
I grab one of them and
beat it out of him. Huh?
That's a great plan, Walter.
That's fucking ingenious,
if I understand it correctly.
It's a Swiss fucking watch.
That's right, Dude.
The beauty of this
is its simplicity.
Once a plan gets too complex,
everything can go wrong.
If there's one thing
I learned in Nam...
(PHONE RINGING)
Dude.
MAN: You are coming
to wooden bridge.
When you cross the bridge,
you throw the bag
from the left window
of the moving car.
You're being watched.
(DIAL TONE HUMS)
Fuck.
What'd he say?
Where's the hand-off?
There is no fucking
hand-off, man.
At the wooden bridge
we throw the money
out of the car.
We throw the money
out of the moving car.
We can't do that, Dude.
That fucks up our plan.
Well, call them up
and explain it
to them, Walter.
Your plan is so
fucking simple,
I'm sure they'll
fucking understand it.
That's the beauty of it.
WALTER: Wooden
bridge, huh?
Throw them the money, Walter.
We're not fucking around, man.
Okay, Dude, the bridge
is coming up. Give me
the ringer, chop-chop.
Fuck that.
Walter, I love you,
but sooner or later you're
gonna have to face the fact
you're a goddamn moron.
Okay, Dude. No time to argue.
Hey, man!
Here's the bridge.
Hey, Walter! Hey, Walter!
Hey, Walter!
Here goes the ringer!
What the fuck?
Okay, Dude, you're wheel.
Hey, man, what the fuck?
At 15 mph, I roll out.
I double back,
grab one of them
and beat it out of him.
The Uzi.
Uzi.
You didn't think I was
rolling out of here
naked, did you?
Walter, please!
Fifteen, Dude! This is it!
Let's take that hill!
Walter!
(TIRES SCREECHING)
(BIKE ENGINES REVVING)
(MOANING)
We have it!
(PANTING)
Fuck it, Dude.
Let's go bowling.
(PHONE RINGING)
(PINS FALLING)
Aitz chaim he, Dude,
as the ex used to say.
What the fuck is that
supposed to mean?
What the fuck are we
gonna tell Lebowski?
Oh, him.
I don't know.
What exactly
is the problem?
The problem is...
What do you mean,
what's the...
There was no...
We didn't...
They're gonna kill
that poor woman, man!
What the fuck
are you talking about?
The poor woman,
that poor slut
kidnapped herself.
Come on, Dude.
You said so yourself.
Man, I said I thought
she kidnapped herself.
You're the one who's
so fucking certain.
That's right, Dude.
100% certain.
They posted the next round
for the tournament.
Donny, shut the fuck...
When do we play?
This Saturday. Quintana and...
Saturday? Well, they'll
have to reschedule.
Walter, what am l
gonna tell Lebowski?
I told that fuck
down at the league office.
Who's in charge of scheduling?
Walter!
Burkhalter.
I told that kraut
a fucking thousand times,
I don't roll on shabbos!
Walter!
They already posted it.
Well, they can
fucking un-post it!
Who gives a shit?
They're gonna kill
that poor woman, man!
What am I gonna
tell Lebowski?
Come on, Dude.
Eventually she'll get tired
of her little game and,
you know, wander on back.
How come you don't roll
on Saturday, Walter?
I'm shomer shabbos.
What's that, Walter?
Yeah, and in
the meantime,
what do I tell Lebowski?
Saturday, Donny, is shabbos,
the Jewish day of rest.
That means I don't work,
I don't drive a car,
I don't fucking
ride in a car,
I don't handle money,
I don't turn on the oven
and I sure as shit
don't fucking roll!
Sheesh.
Shomer shabbos!
Walter, how am I gonna...
Shomer·u··· shabbos!
Oh, fuck! That's it.
I'm out of here.
Oh, come on, Dude.
(lNAUDIBLE)
Dude! Dude!
You just tell him...
Tell him we made the drop
and everything went,
you know...
Oh, yeah.
How'd it go?
Went all right.
Dude's car got
a little dinged up.
Walter, we didn't make
the fucking hand-off, man!
They didn't get
the fucking money!
And they're gonna...
They're gonna...
They're gonna kill
that poor woman.
that poor woman!
Walter, if you can't
ride in a car,
then how do you get
around on shabbos?
Really, Dude,
you surprise me.
They're not gonna
kill shit.
They're not gonna do shit.
What can they do to her?
Bunch of fucking amateurs.
And meanwhile,
look at the bottom line.
Who's sitting on a million
fucking dollars?
Am I wrong?
Walter.
Who's got a fucking
million fucking dollars
sitting in the trunk of our car?
Our car, Walter?
And what do they got?
My dirty undies.
My fucking whites!
(PHONE RINGING)
(CLEARS THROAT)
Say, Dude?
Where is your car?
Who's got your
undies, Walter?
Where's your car, Dude?
You don't know,
Walter?
WALTER: It was parked
in a handicap zone.
Perhaps they towed it.
(PHONE RINGING)
You fucking know
it's been stolen.
Well, certainly that's
a possibility, Dude.
Oh, fuck it.
Where you going, Dude?
I'm going home, Donny.
Phone's ringing, Dude.
Thank you, Donny!
(PHONE RINGING)
(PHONE STOPS RINGING)
Yeah.
سبز؛ یه جاها هم قهوه‌ای.
رنگ زنگ آهن
Green with some brown,
rust coloration.
چیز با ارزشی هم توی ماشین بود؟
And was there anything
of value in the car?
اوه. البته..
Oh, yeah.
جعبه نوار.. چنتا نوار کریدنس..یه چیزم بود..
A tape deck, some Creedence
tapes, and there was a...
کیف سامسونتم..
My briefcase.
توی سامسونت؟
In the briefcase?
برگه
Papers.
برگه فقط..
Just papers.
می‌دونی برگه‌هام.
برگه‌های کار و تجارتم..
You know, my papers,
business papers.
مشغول به چه کاری هستید قربان؟
بیکار هستم.
And what do you do, sir?
I'm unemployed.
(PHONE RINGING)
فرشم هم به سرقت رفته درضمن.
My rug was also stolen.
فرشتون توی ماشین بوده؟
Your rug was in the car?
نه. اینجا.
No. Here.
حادثه‌های مجزا!
Separate incidents.
(ANSWERING MACHINE CLICKS)
دوود اینجا نیست.
DUDE ON MACHINE:
The Dude is not in.
از این ماشین‌های سرقت شده، پیداشون هم می‌کنید عموما؟
Do you find them much,
these stolen cars?
گاهی وقتا.
Sometimes.
خیلی به نوار کاست‌ها امیدی نیست اما..
Wouldn't hold out much hope
for the tape deck though.
یا نوارای کریدنس..
Or the Creedence.
(ANSWERING MACHINE BEEPS)
درمورد... سامسونت‌ه چطور؟
What about the briefcase?
آقای لبوفسکی.
من می‌خوام شما رو ببینم.
WOMAN: Mr. Lebowski,
I'd like to see you.
وقتی رسیدید زنگ بزنید و من ماشین رو می‌فرستم..
Call when you get home
and I'll send a car for you.
اسم من ماود لبوفسکی هست.
من فرش شما رو بردم..
My name is Maude Lebowski.
I'm the one who took your rug.
چه عالی!
فک کنم می‌شه پرونده این یکی رو بست اقلن..
Well, guess we can
close the file
on that one.
(DOOR CLOSES)
(WOMAN CHANTING)
(THUDDING)
(SQUEAKING)
(YELLS)
(WOMAN SPEAKING
FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
چند لحظه دیگه خدمت می‌رسم میام، آقای لبوفسکی..
I'll be with you in
a moment, Mr. Lebowski.
(WOMAN CHANTING)
(lNDISTINCT CHATTERING)
آیا فرم فمینی شما رو معذب کرده آقای لبوفسکی؟
Does the female form
make you uncomfortable,
Mr. Lebowski?
ئه این عکس اون هست؟
به نوعی. بله.
Is that what this
is a picture of?
In a sense, yes.
از هنر من بعنوان هنری بسیار واژنی یاد شده.
My art has been commended
as being strongly vaginal,
که برای بعضی مردها تحملش سخت هست.
which bothers some men.
حتا خود کلمه‌ش هم بعضی مردها رو معذب می‌کنه..
The word itself makes
some men uncomfortable.
مهبل.
جدی؟
Vagina.
Oh, yeah?
بله. اونها تمایل ندارند که بشنوند اون رو
و گفتنش براشون سخت هست.
Yes, they don't like
hearing it and find it
difficult to say,
حال که بدون پلک زدن
whereas without
batting an eye,
یک مرد به آلتش یا دستش یا جانسونش اشاره می‌کنه..
a man will refer to his dick,
or his rod or his johnson.
«جانسون»؟
"Johnson"?
خیل خب آقای لبوفسکی.
بیاید به بررسی مسائل بپردازیم.
All right, Mr. Lebowski,
let's get down to cases.
پدر من گفتند که قبول کردند شما فرش رو به شما بدن
My father told me he agreed
to let you have the rug,
اما از اونجایی که این هدیه‌ای از طرف من به مادر مرحومم بوده
ایشون چنین حقی نداشتن که اونو به کسی بدن..
but as it was a gift
from me to my late mother,
it was not his to give.
حالا؛ صورتتون رو پاک کنید.
Now, your face.
راجع به این آدم‌ربایی.
As for this kidnapping.
چی؟
Huh?
من کاملا در جریان هستم.
همچنین می‌دونم که شما نقش حامل رو بازی کردید..
Yes, I know all about it,
and I know that you acted
as courier.
بذارید چیزی رو بهتون بگم.
بوی قضیه تا بهشت اعلا میاد..
Let me tell you something.
The whole thing stinks to
high heaven.
بله. درسته. ولی بذارید چیزی رو راجع به فرش به شما بگم..
Yeah, right, but let me
explain something about
the rug.
شما به سکس علاقه‌دارید آقای لبوفسکی؟
Do you like sex,
Mr. Lebowski?
جانم؟
سکس؛ جلوه فیزیکی عشق. معاشقه..
Excuse me?
Sex, the physical act
of love. Coitus.
بهش علاقه دارید؟
راستش راجع به فرشم می‌خواستم بگم..
Do you like it?
I was talking
about my rug.
به سکس علاقه ندارید؟
You're not interested in sex?
ینی معاشقه؟
منم دوستش دارم.
You mean coitus?
I like it, too.
میان مردان افسانه‌ای راجع به فمنیست‌ها وجود داره که
می‌گه ما از سکس متنفریم.
It's a male myth about
feminists that we hate sex.
سکس می‌تونه یه حرکت طبیعی و دلچسب باشه.
It can be a natural,
zesty enterprise.
اما، بعضی افراد هستند
However, there are
some people,
در مردان بهشون satyriasis
و در زنها بهشون nymphmania می‌گند
it is called
satyriasis in men,
nymphomania in women,
که بی‌اختیار و بدون لذت وارد اون می‌شن.
who engage in it compulsively
and without joy.
اوه. نه..
اوه. بله؛ آقای لبوفسکی
Oh, no.
Oh, yes, Mr. Lebowski.
این روان‌های بیچاره به معنی واقعی کلمه نمی‌تونند معاشقه کنند.
These unfortunate souls
cannot love, in the true
sense of the word.
آشنای مشترک ما، بانی، از این دسته هست.
Our mutual acquaintance,
Bunny, is one of these.
ببین، ماود.
Listen, Maude,
من متاسفم که نامادری‌ت نیمفو هست.
I'm sorry if your stepmother
is a nympho,
ولی متوجه نیستم این مساله چه ربطی به
but, you know, I don't see
what this has to do with...
کالوها هم دارید؟
یه نگاهی به این بندازید، قربان.
You have any Kahlua?
Take a look at this, sir.
دوود: ئه من اینو می‌شناسم..
DUDE: Oh, I know that guy.
اون نیهیلیست‌ه..
He's a nihilist.
«کار هانگوس»
"Karl Hungus."
(lCE CUBES CLINKING)
سلام..
سلام.
Hi.
Hello.
کارفرمای من وگفته بید ئییی کابل شما خراب وزیته
Mein dispatcher says
there is something
wrong with dein Kabel.
بله! بیاید تو!!
Yeah. Come on in.
من راستش خیلی هم مطمئن نیستم مشکل کابل‌مون چیه.
I'm not really sure
exactly what's really
wrong with the cable.
هاا مَ واسه همین ای‌جا بیدم جیگر.
هاا ای مَ متخصص بیدم.
That's why they sent me.
I am an expert.
تلوزیون اینجاست.
The TV's in here.
ایشون رو بجا میارید البته.
هلگا، ایی ابزارای مَ رَ وردا بیا.
You recognize her,
of course.
Helga, bring my tools.
این دوست من شری‌ه..
That's my friend Sherry.
اومد اینجا از حموم استفاده کنه..
She just came over
to use the shower.
داستان مبتذل‌ه..
The story is ludicrous.
ها ای اسم م ُ کارل بیده.
ئی منم متخصص وزیتم.
My name is Karl.
lch bin expert.
شما احتمالن برای تعمیر کابل اومدید..
You must be here
to fix the cable.
خدایا..
می‌تونید تصور کنید ازینجا به بعدش رو..
Lord, you can imagine
where it goes from here.
کابلشون رو درست می‌کنه؟
He fixes the cable?
چرت نگو لطفا، جفری!
Don't be fatuous, Jeffrey.
اصلا برای من مهم نیست که این زن راهی در پیشه‌ی پورنوگرافی برای خودش انتخاب کرده
Little matter to me that
this woman chose to pursue
a career in pornography,
یا اینکه با جکی تریهورن «می‌خوابه»
nor that she has been
banging Jackie Treehorn,
اگه از ادبیات زمانه خودمون استفاده کنیم..
to use the parlance
of our times.
However,
I am one of the two trustees
of the Lebowski Foundation,
the other being my father.
The foundation takes
youngsters from Watts and...
Shit, yeah. The achievers.
Little Lebowski Urban
Achievers, yes, and proud
we are of all of them.
I asked my father about
his withdrawal of $1 million
from the foundation account,
and he told me
about this abduction,
but I tell you
it is preposterous.
This compulsive fornicator
is taking my father for
the proverbial ride.
Yeah, but my...
I'm getting to your rug.
My father and l
don't get along.
He doesn't approve
of my lifestyle and,
needless to say,
I don't approve of his.
However, I hardly
wish to make my father's
embezzlement a police matter.
So I'm proposing that you
try to recover the money
from the people
you delivered it to.
Well, I could do that.
If you successfully do so,
I will compensate you
to the tune of 10% of
the recovered sum.
A hundred...
Thousand. Yes.
Bones or clams or
whatever you call them.
Yeah, but what about my...
Your rug, yes.
Well, with that money
you can buy any
number of rugs
that don't have sentimental
value for me.
And I am sorry about
that crack on the jaw.
Oh, that's fine.
That doesn't even...
Here's the name and
number of a doctor who
will look at it for you.
You will receive no bill.
He's a good man
and thorough.
(STUTTERS)
That's thoughtful but...
Please see him, Jeffrey.
He's a good man and thorough.
Oh, well, all right.
So he says, "My wife's
a pain in the ass.
"She's always busting
my frigging agates.
"My daughter's married
to a loser bastard.
"l got a rash
so bad on my ass
I can't even sit down.
"But you know me,
I can't complain."
(LAUGHING)
Oh, fucking A, man.
I got a rash, man. Fucking A.
I gotta tell you, Tone, man,
earlier today I was really
feeling shitty, man.
Really down in the dumps.
Lost a little money...
Hey, you know what?
Forget about it, huh?
Forget about it.
Yeah, fuck it, man.
You can't be worried
about that shit.
Life goes on, man.
Well, home, sweet home,
Mr. L.
TONY: Hey, yo. Come here.
Who's your friend
in the Volkswagen?
Huh?
TONY: Yeah.
He followed us here.
When did he start...
Whoa! What the fuck?
Get in the limo,
you son of a bitch!
No arguments!
Hey! Hey! Careful, man!
There's a beverage here!
Start talking,
and talk fast,
you lousy bum.
We've been frantically
trying to reach you, Dude.
Where is my goddamn money,
you bum?
Well, we... I don't...
They did not receive
the money, you nitwit!
They did not
receive the money!
Her life was
in your hands!
This is our concern, Dude.
No, man.
Nothing is fucked here.
Nothing is fucked?
No, man.
The goddamn plane
has crashed into
the mountain!
Man, come on.
Who are you gonna
believe, those guys or...
We dropped off the damn money.
We?
l, the royal we.
You know. The editorial...
I dropped off the money
exactly as per...
Look, man, I've got
certain information.
All right?
Certain things have
come to light and...
You know, has it ever
occurred to you
that instead of, you know,
running around, blaming me...
You know, given the nature
of all this new shit,
you know, this could be
a lot more complex...
I mean, it's not just...
It might not be just such
a simple... You know?
What in God's holy name
are you blathering about?
Well, I'll tell you what
I'm blathering about.
I've got information, man.
New shit has come to light.
And, shit, man,
she kidnapped herself.
Well, sure, man.
Look at it. You know?
A young trophy wife,
in the parlance of
our times, you know.
She owes money
all over town, including
to known pornographers.
And that's cool.
That's cool.
I'm saying she
needs money, man.
And, you know,
of course they're gonna
say they didn't get it
because she wants more, man.
She's gotta feed the monkey.
I mean...
Hasn't that ever
occurred to you, man?
Sir?
No, Mr. Lebowski,
it had not occurred
to me.
That had not
occurred to us, Dude.
Well, okay, you know?
You guys aren't privy
to all the new shit,
so, you know...
But, hey, that's what you...
That's what you pay me for.
(CHUCKLES)
Speaking of which,
do you think that you could
give me my $20,000 in cash?
My concern is, and
I've gotta check it
with my accountant,
that this might bump me up
into a higher tax...
Brandt, give him
the envelope.
Oh, well, if you've
already got the check
made out, that's cool.
BRANDT: We received this
this morning.
Since you have
failed to achieve,
even in the modest task
which was your charge,
since you have
stolen my money,
unrepentantly
betrayed my trust,
I have no choice
but to tell these bums
to do whatever is necessary
to recover their money
from you, Jeffrey Lebowski.
And with Brandt as my witness,
I will tell you this,
any further harm
visited upon Bunny
will be visited tenfold
upon your head.
By God, sir,
I will not abide another toe.
I hear the cottonwoods
whispering above
بابا انگشت خودش که نبوده دوود.
That wasn't her toe, Dude.
انگشت کی بوده پس والتر؟
من از کجا بدونم؟
Whose toe was it, Walter?
How the fuck should I know?
فقط می‌دونم هیچی بر این دلالت نمی‌کنه که
I do know that nothing
about it indicates...
لاک ناخنش، والتر.
The nail polish, Walter.
خیل‌خوب دود.
Fine, Dude
انگار مثلا نمیشه یه لاک ناخن بگیری، بزنی رو انگشت یکی دیگه..
As if it's impossible to get
some nail polish, apply it
to someone else's toe...
Someone else...
Pinking shears.
آخه از کجا باهاس گیر بی..
Where the fuck are
they gonna get...
انشگت می‌خوای؟
یه انگشت من خودم برات میارم.
You want a toe?
I can get you a toe.
باور کن. کلی راه هست دوود.
Believe me,
there are ways, Dude.
ندونیم بهتره. باور کن.
آره، ولی والتر
You don't wanna know
about it, believe me.
Yeah, but, Walter...
جهنم. اصن می‌تونم تا ۳ بعد از ظهر برات یک انگشت گیر بیارم.
«با لاک ناخن»
Hell, I could get you a toe
by 3:00 this afternoon
with nail polish.
آماتورای بدبخت.
والتر..
These fucking amateurs.
Walter...
یه انگشتی واسه ما می‌فرستن*
ما قراره از ترس برینیم تو شلوارمون.
They send us a toe,
we're supposed to shit
ourselves with fear.
یا عیسی مسیح.
والتر..
Jesus Christ!
Walter...
نکته اینجاست که..
اینا قراره بکشن دختره‌رو والتر..
The point is...
They're gonna
kill her, Walter,
و بعدش قراره منو بکشن..
and then they're
gonna kill me.
ببین دود اینا همش..
Dude, that's...
این فقط حرف از رو استرس‌ه، رفیق.
That's just the
stress talking, man.
ببین تاحالا، اونچه که بنظر من می‌رسه، یه سری جرم بدون قربانی داشتیم.
Now, so far we have
what appears to me to be
a series of victimless crimes.
انگشته چی پس؟
ریدم به قبر هرچی انگشته!
What about the toe?
Forget about the fucking toe!
ببخشید اقا.
ممکنه یکم آرومتر صحبت کنید؟
Excuse me, sir.
Could you please
keep your voices down?
اینجا یه رستوران خانوادگیه.
This is a family restaurant.
اوه خواهشا، عزیز.
جهت اطلاعتون
Oh, please! Dear,
for your information,
دیوان عالی .....
the Supreme Court
has roundly rejected
prior restraint.
بیخیال والتر این قضیه ...نیست
Come on. Walter,
this is not a First
Amendment thing, man.
قربان اگه صداتون رو پایین نیارید مجبور می‌شم ازتون خواهش کنم اینجا رو ترک کنید
Sir, if you don't calm down,
I'm gonna have to
ask you to leave.
خانم‌م. من دوستایی داره که با صورت تو لجن جون دادن
Lady, I got buddies
who died face down
in the muck
تا من و تو ازین رستوران خانوادگی لذت ببریم.
so that you and I can enjoy
this family restaurant!
خیلی خب اصن. من رفتم.
ای بابا. دوود. پا نشو برو رفیق.
All right,
I'm out of here.
Hey, Dude, don't go away, man.
این رو همه‌ی ما تاثیر گذاره. اینا آزادی‌های اساسی ماست.
Come on. This affects
all of us, man! lt's
our basic freedoms!
من که می‌مونم.
I'm staying.
قهوه‌مو تموم می‌کنم.
I'm finishing my coffee.
از قهوه‌م لذت می‌برم.
Enjoying my coffee.
(WHALE SONG PLAYING ON TAPE)
(PHONE RINGING)
(STIFLED COUGHING)
(ANSWERING MACHINE CLICKS)
دوود خونه نیست.
DUDE ON MACHINE:
The Dude is not in.
بعد بوق پیغام بذارید. یه دقیقه بیشتر طول نمی‌کشه.
£eave a message
after the beep.
It takes a minute.
(BEEPS)
Mr. Lebowski,
this is Duty O·ce·
Rolvaag of the LAPD.
ما ماشینتون رو پیدا کردیم.
We've recovered
your automobile.
It can be claimed
at the North Hollywood
Auto Circus there on Victory.
Their hours there are...
عجـــب. ای عجــــب.
Far out, man. Far fucking out!
(BANGING)
آهای. اینجا ملک خصوصی‌ه حاجی.
Hey! This is a private
residence, man.
(CHATTERING)
آخی. چه موش‌خرمای نازی.
Oh, nice marmot.
(SNARLING)
(SHRIEKING)
(SQUEALING)
هااا این پوولا کجا بیده لبوفسکی؟
مااا این پولارِ وخوایم لبوفسکی.
(WITH GERMAN ACCENT)
Where is the money, Lebowski?
We wants the money, Lebowski!
(SHRIEKING)
(PANICKED STAMMERING)
فک وکردی شوخی از خودمون در وکردیم یا بامزه بازی در ویاریم؟
You think we are kidding or
making with the funny stuff?
ما وتونیم کارایی از خودمون در وکونیم که تو خواب‌م نودیده باشی لبوفسکی..
We could do things
you haven't dreamed of,
Lebowski.
هااا. ما به هیچی اعتقاد نداشته بیدیم لبوفسکی.
هیچی!
Ja, we believes in nothing.
We believes in nothing,
Lebowski. Nothing!
فردا هم ویایم و اییی جانسونت َ از جا وَکَنیم.
And tomorrow we come back
and we cut off yourjohnson.
ببخشید؟
وگفتم جانسونتَ از جاا وکنیم!
Excuse me?
I said, we cut off
yourjohnson!
هاا به این فقط فک وکن لبوفسکی.
Just think about that,
Lebowski.
هااا ای دست ریزه‌میزه تَ لبوفسکی..
Your wiggly penis, Lebowski.
هاا. شاید لگدش وکردیم و له وشد لبوفسکی..
Ja. Maybe we stomp on it
and squish it.
(GLASS SHATTERS)
(SIGHS)
MAN: It was discovered
last night in Van Nuys
lodged against an abutment.
DUDE: Oh, man. Lodged where?
You're lucky she didn't
get chopped, Mr. Lebowski.
Oh, man!
Must've been
a joyride situation.
They abandoned the vehicle
once they hit the retaining
wall.
Oh, my fucking
briefcase, man!
It's not here! Shit!
Yeah, I saw that
on the report. Sorry.
You gotta get in
on the other side.
The side view was found
on the road by the car.
You're lucky they left
the tape deck though,
and the Creedence.
Oh, Jesus!
What's that smell, man?
Yeah. It's probably
a vagrant slept in the car.
Or maybe just used it
as a toilet and moved on.
Hey, man,
are you gonna find these guys?
Or, you know, I mean...
You got any promising
leads or...
Leads?
Yeah. Sure.
I'll just check with the boys
down at the crime lab.
They got four more detectives
working on the case.
They got us working in shifts!
(LAUGHING HYSTERICALLY)
Leads!
DUDE: My only hope is that
the big Lebowski kills me
before the Germans
can cut my dick off.
Leads!
ببین دوود؛ این دیگه خیلی چرته خدایی..
Now, that is just
ridiculous, Dude.
هیچکی قرار نیست آلتت رو از جا بکنه..
No one's going to
cut your dick off.
ممنونم، والتر.
نه که فقط چون من می‌گم اینطوری باشه‌ البته..
Thank you, Walter.
Not if I have anything
to say about it.
مرسی والتر..
Thank you, Walter.
این یه حس امنیتی به من می‌ده..
دوود؟
That makes me
feel very secure.
Dude?
این یه گرمای درونی به من می‌بخشه دوست من..
دووود؟
That makes me feel
very warm inside, man.
Dude?
کل این بساط لعنتی
This whole fucking thing.
من می‌شد فقط اینجا نشسته باشم و
چنتا لکه نجاست رو قالی‌م باشه..
I could be sitting here
with just pee stains on
my rug.
ولی می‌دونی چیه.. ولی حالا
آلمانای لعنتی..
But no, man,
I got a, you know...
Yeah. Fucking Germans.
هیچی عوض نمی‌شه..
Nothing changes.
نازی‌های عوضی..
اونا نازی بودن دوود؟
Fucking Nazis.
They were Nazis, Dude?
ای بابا دانی..
اونا تهدید به اخته کردن کردند..
Oh, come on, Donny.
They were threatening
castration!
خب..؟
قراره بحثای چرت و مزخرف بکنیم؟
Uh-huh.
Are we gonna
split hairs here?
نه.
اشتباه میگم؟
No.
Am I wrong?
خب اون ن..
دوست من، اونا نیهیلیست بودن دوست من..
Well, he didn't...
Man, they were
nihilists, man.
هی داشتن می‌گفتن به هیچ‌چی اعتقاد ندارن..
They kept saying they
believed in nothing.
نیهیلست..
Nihilists.
یا ابالافضل..
Fuck me.
I mean, say what you
want about the tenets of
national socialism, Dude.
At least it's an ethos.
Yeah.
و، درضمن. فراموش نکنیم
فراموش نکنیم دوود
And, also,
let's not forget...
Let's not forget, Dude,
که نگه داشتم حیوان،
موش آبزی
that keeping wildlife,
an amphibious rodent,
برای، چمی‌دونم، مصارف شهری
for, you know,
domestic...
داخل شهر
Within the city...
این هم قانونی نیست..
چیه حالا نگهبان جنگل شدی الان؟
That ain't legal,
either.
What are you,
a fucking park ranger now?
نه فقط می‌خوام بگم که..
No! I'm just
trying to...
کی چیکار موش خرمای لعنتی داره؟
Who gives a shit
about the fucking marmot?
ما داریم هم‌دردی می کنیم اینجا، دوود.
گه به این همدردی..
We are sympathizing
here, Dude.
Fuck sympathy.
من به همدردی شما نیاز ندارم دوست من..
من جانسون عزیزم رو می‌خوام..
I don't need your
fucking sympathy, man.
I need my fucking johnson.
اونو واسه چی می‌خوای دوود؟
تو باید خودتو جمع و جور کنی رفیق!
What do you need
that for, Dude?
You have got to
buck up, man!
این انرژی منفی رو نمی‌تونی با خودت تو تورنومنت بیاری..
You cannot drag this
negative energy into
the tournament.
ریدم به ترنمنت..
ریدم به تو اصلا، والتر!
Fuck the tournament.
Fuck you, Walter.
ریدی به تورنومنت؟!
Fuck the tournament?
خیل خب دوود. می‌بینم که نمی‌خوای اصلا سر حال بیای..
Okay, Dude. I can see
you don't want to be
cheered up here.
بیا بریم دانی.
Come on, Donny.
Let's go get us a lane.
Another Caucasian, Gary.
Right, Dude.
Friends like these,
huh, Gary?
That's right, Dude.
(ORCHESTRAL MUSIC
PLAYING ON STEREO)
See them tumbling down
Pledging their love
to the ground
Lonely, but free,
I'll be found
You got a good
sarsaparilla?
Sioux City Sarsaparilla?
Yeah. That's a good one.
How're you doing there,
Dude?
Not too good, man.
One of those days, huh?
Yeah.
Well, a wiser fellow
than myself once said,
"Sometimes you eat
the bear and..."
(GLASS SETTLING)
Much obliged.
"Sometimes the bear,
well, he eats you."
That some kind of
Eastern thing?
Far from it.
I like your style, Dude.
Oh, well, I dig
your style, too, man.
Got a whole cowboy thing
going.
Thank you.
There's just one thing, Dude.
What's that?
Do you have to use
so many cuss words?
What the fuck are
you talking about?
Okay, Dude. Have it your way.
Take her easy, Dude.
Yeah. Thanks, man.
(MAN WHISTLING ON STEREO)
Call for you, Dude.
Hello?
MAUDE: Jeffrey, you have
not gone to the doctor.
Oh, yeah, no.
No, I haven't yet.
I'd like to see you
immediately.
Oh?
خب پس. لبوفسکی تویی
آره
So, you're Lebowski.
Yeah.
ماود خیلی چیزا ازت برام گفته
Maude has told me
all about you.
الان میاد.
بشین.
She'll be back in a minute.
Sit down.
نوشیدنی چیزی می‌خوای؟
آره. مرسی. سپیدروس لطفا.
Do you want a drink?
Yeah, sure. White Russian.
بار اونوره.
The bar's over there.
خب شغلت چیه لبوفسکی؟
تو کودوم گهی هستی حاجی؟
So, what do you do,
Lebowski?
Who the fuck are you, man?
(GIGGLING)
دوست ماودی‌جونم.
آره؟ دوست ِ دستْ جر خورده‌ش؟
Just a friend of Maudie's.
Yeah? The friend with
the cleft asshole?
(GIGGLING)
تو چی‌کار می‌کنی؟
اوا. هیچی خیلی.
What do you do?
Oh, nothing much.
(GIGGLING)
سلام جفری.
سلام.
Hello, Jeffrey.
Hello.
ئه. چطوری؟
ببین ماود.
Yeah. How are you?
Listen, Maude.
من باید که
I got to
استعفا بدم، یا هرچی.
tender my resignation
or whatever
انگار مادرت جدی جدی ربوده شده بود واقعا.
because looks like
your mother really
was kidnapped after all.
قطعا که ربوده هم نشده.
She most certainly was not.
ای بابا. ببین، چرا هر از چندگاهی گوش نمی‌دی به حرف ملت؟
Hey, man, why don't you
fucking listen
occasionally?
شاید یه چیزی دستگیرت شد. حالا من..
You might learn something.
Now, I got...
لطفا بهش نگو «مادر من».
(KNOX GIGGLING)
Please don't call her
my mother.
اون به طور قطع مجرم هست نه قربانی.
She's most definitely
the perpetrator and
not the victim.
دارم بهت می‌گم، ادله خیلی قوی دارم.
I'm telling you, I've got
pretty definitive evidence.
از کی؟
از همون سردسته‌شون. اولی.
From who?
From the main guy, Uli.
اولی کونکل؟ سردسته‌شون تو ....؟
Uli Kunkel? Her costar
in the beaver picture?
منظورت مهبل‌ه؟
ینی، می‌گم می‌شناسی یارو رو؟
You mean vagina?
I mean, you know the guy?
احتمالا خودمم معرفیشون کردم  تا اونجا که یادمه.
I might have introduced them,
for all I know.
اولی رو یادته تو؟
Do you remember Uli?
تو کار موزیکه. یه گروهی داشت، اتوبان.
He's a musician.
Used to have a group,
Autobahn.
به این سی‌دیای من نگاه کن. آخرای دهه ۷۰ یه آلبوم بیرون دادن.
Look in my LP's.
They released one
album in the late '70s.
ماود: موزیکشون تکنوپاپ مانندیه.
MAUDE: Their music is
sort of a techno pop.
پس اونه که نقش رباینده‌رو بازی می‌کنه؟
خب آره..
So he's pretending
to be the abductor?
Well, yeah.
ببین جفری. شما نمیای کسی رو که آشنایی باهاش بدزدی.
Look, Jeffrey, you don't
really kidnap someone
you're acquainted with.
ایده اصلا این هست که گروگان نتونه بفهمه کی بودی بعد اینکه آزادش کردی.
The whole idea is that the
hostage can't identify you
after you've let them go.
خب معلومه. می‌دونم اینو!
Well, I know that.
(GIGGLES)
این یارو چه مرگشه؟
کیه؟
What the fuck is
with this guy?
Who is he?
ناکس هرینگتون. ویدیو ساز.
Knox Harrington,
the video artist.
پس پولا دست اوولی‌یه.
So, Uli has the money.
راستش، نه دقیقا.
Well, no, not exactly.
ببین ماود این یه موضوع خیلی پیچیده‌س.
This is a very complicated
case, Maude.
(PHONE RINGING)
حواست هست، پر از فراز، پر از فرود.
You know, a lot of ins,
a lot of outs,
پر از هرچی.
a lot of what-have-yous
and a lot of strands
to keep in my head, man.
You know, a lot of strands
in the old Duder's head.
Hello?
If Uli doesn't have it,
then who does?
It's Sandra
about the Biennale.
Look. I have to take this.
Do you still have that
doctor's number?
No, really, it's not even
bruised anymore.
Oh, please, Jeffrey.
I don't want to be responsible
for any delayed aftereffects.
(SPEAKING FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
Aftereffects?
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING ON STEREO)
Could you slide your shorts
down, Mr. Lebowski, please?
Mmm?
No, no, man.
She hit me right here.
I understand.
Could you slide your
shorts down, please?
(LOOKIN' OUT MY BACK DOOR
PLAYING ON STEREO)
Just got home from lllinois
Locked the front door, oh, boy
Got to sit down,
take a rest on the porch
Imagination sets in
Pretty soon I'm singin'
Doo, doo, doo
Looking out my back door
Keeping mighty cool.
There's a giant
doing cartwheels
A statue wearing high heels
Look at all the
happy creatures
Dancing on the lawn
A dinosaur Victrola
listening to Buck Owens
(SQUEALING)
Doo, doo, doo
Looking out my back door
(HORN HONKING)
Tambourines and elephants
are playing in the band
Doo, doo, doo
Wondrous apparition
provided by magician
Doo, doo, doo
Looking out my back door
Tambourines and elephants
are playing in the band
Won't you take a ride
on the flying spoon?
Doo, doo, doo
Bother me tomorrow
Today I'll buy no sorrows
Doo, doo, doo
Looking out my back door
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
He lives in
North Hollywood on Radford,
near the ln-N-Out Burger.
No, the ln-N-Out
Burger's on Camrose.
Near the ln-N-Out Burger.
Those are good burgers,
Walter.
Shut the fuck up, Donny.
The kid is in the ninth
grade, Dude.
And his father is...
Are you ready for this?
His father is
Arthur Digby Sellers.
Who the fuck is that?
Who the fuck is
Arthur Digby Sellers?
Who the...
Have you ever
heard of a little show
called Branded, Dude?
Yes, yes, l...
"All but one man
died there at
Bitter Creek."
I know the fucking show,
Walter. So what?
Fucking Arthur Digby Sellers
wrote 156 episodes, Dude.
The bulk of the series.
Oh.
Not exactly
a lightweight.
No.
And yet his son
is a fucking dunce.
Anyway, we'll go there
after the what-have-you.
We'll brace the kid.
Should be a pushover.
We'll be near
the ln-N-Out Burger.
Shut the fuck up, Donny!
(MAN SHUSHING)
We'll go out there,
we'll brace the kid.
He should be a pushover.
We'll get that fucking
million dollars back,
if he hasn't
spent it already.
A million fucking clams.
And, yes,
we'll be near the...
ln-N-Out.
Shh! Shh!
Some burgers, some beers.
A few laughs.
Our fucking troubles
are over, Dude.
Oh, fuck me, man.
That kid's already spent
all the money, man.
New Vette? Hardly, Dude.
I'd say he still has
$060,000, $070,000 left,
depending on the options.
Wait in the car, Donny.
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
WOMAN: Yes?
Pilar?
My name is Walter Sobchak.
This is my associate,
Jeffrey Lebowski.
We came to talk
about little Larry.
May we come in?
Yes, yes.
Thank you.
That's him, Dude.
(MACHINERY HUMMING)
And a good day
to you, sir!
Sit down, please.
Larry, sweetie,
the man is here!
Is he...
Does he still write?
Oh, no, no.
He has health problems.
Uh-huh.
Sir, I just want to say
that we're both,
on a personal level,
really enormous fans.
Branded, especially
the early episodes,
was truly a source
of inspiration.
PILAR: Sweetie, sit down.
This man is the police.
Oh, no, ma'am. We didn't want
to give the impression that
we were police, exactly.
We're hoping it
won't be necessary
to call the police.
But that's up to
little Larry here.
Isn't it, Larry?
Is this your homework,
Larry?
Look, man, it...
Dude. Please?
Is this your
homework, Larry?
Just ask him about
the car, man.
Is this yours, Larry?
Is this your homework,
Larry?
Is that your car out front?
Is this your homework, Larry?
We know it's his
fucking homework!
Where's the fucking money,
you little brat?
Look, Larry, have you
ever heard of Vietnam?
For Christ's sake, Walter.
You are entering
a world of pain, son.
We know that this is
your homework. We know
that you stole the car.
And the fucking money.
And the fucking money!
And we know that
this is your homework!
We're gonna cut
your dick off, Larry.
You're killing
your father, Larry.
All right.
This is pointless.
Okay, time for Plan B.
You might want to watch out
that front window, Larry.
Son, this is what happens
when you fuck a stranger
in the ass!
A little language
problem here.
Little prick's
stonewalling me.
Walter.
What are you doing, man?
What are you doing?
Here you go, Larry.
You see what happens?
You see what happens, Larry?
Oh, great.
This is what happens
when you fuck a stranger
in the ass, Larry.
This is what happens, Larry.
You see what happens, Larry?
You see what happens
when you fuck a stranger
in the ass?
This is what happens!
(GLASS SHATTERING)
You see what happens, Larry?
Do you see what happens,
Larry, when you fuck
a stranger in the ass?
This is what happens, Larry!
MAN: My car! My baby!
This is what happens
when you fuck a stranger...
What the fuck are you
doing, man? Stop it!
Hey, man.
I just bought that
fucking car last week!
Whoa, whoa, whoa!
I'm sorry!
I'm gonna fucking kill you!
I just bought the
fucking car last week!
Come on, man.
I'll kill your
fucking car, man!
No, no. Hey, hey,
that's not his! Hey!
God damn it!
Whoa! Oh, no!
MAN: Fuck you!
Man. No.
You like that? Fuck you!
I'll kill your fucking car!
DUDE: No. No, no. No.
(SPANISH MUSIC
PLAYING ON RADIO)
I accept your apology.
No, I just want to handle it
by myself from now on.
No. No. No!
That has nothing
to do with it.
Yes, the car made it home.
You're calling me at home.
No, Walter, it did not look
like Larry was about to crack!
Well, that's your perception.
You know, Walter,
you're right.
There is an unspoken
message here.
lt's, "Fuck you!
Leave me the fuck alone!"
Yeah, I'll be at practice.
Pin your diapers on,
Lebowski.
Jackie Treehorn
wants to see you.
Jackie Treehorn knows
which Lebowski you are,
Lebowski.
Jackie Treehorn
wants to see the
deadbeat Lebowski.
You're not dealing
with morons here.
(MAN CHANTING)
Hello, Dude.
Thanks for coming.
I'm Jackie Treehorn.
This is quite a pad
you got here, man.
Completely unspoiled.
What's your drink, Dude?
A White Russian. Thanks.
White Russian.
How's the smut business,
Jackie?
I wouldn't know, Dude.
I deal in publishing,
entertainment,
political advocacy.
Which one's Logjammin'?
Yes, regrettably, it's true.
Standards have fallen
in adult entertainment.
It's video, Dude.
Now that we're competing
with those amateurs,
we can't afford to invest
in little extras like story,
production value, feelings.
You know,
people forget that the brain
is the biggest erogenous zone.
On you maybe.
Of course, you have to take
the good with the bad.
New technology permits us
to do very exciting things
in interactive
erotic software.
Wave of the future, Dude.
100% electronic.
Well, I still jerk off
manually.
(CHUCKLES)
Of course you do.
I can see you're anxious
for me to get to the point.
Well, here it is, Dude.
Where's Bunny?
Well, I thought you
might know that, man.
Why would l?
She only ran off
to get away from that
rather sizable debt to me.
No, she didn't run off.
She's been...
I heard that kidnapping story,
so save it.
I know you're mixed up
in all this, Dude.
And I don't care
what you're trying
to get from the husband.
That's your business.
All I'm saying is I want mine.
Yeah, right, man.
I mean, there are a lot of
facets to this,
(PHONE RINGING)
a lot of interested parties.
Excuse me.
Yeah?
Oh, yeah?
Where is that?
All right. Yeah.
Excuse me.
(DOOR CLOSES)
Forgive me.
No problemo, man.
So, if I can find your money,
what's in it for the Dude?
Well, of course,
there's that to discuss.
You want a refill?
Yeah, does the pope
shit in the woods?
10% finder's fee.
That all right?
Okay. Done, Jackie.
I dig the way
you do business, man.
Your money is being
held by a kid named
Larry Sellers.
He lives in North Hollywood
on Radford,
by the ln-N-Out Burger.
Fucking brat.
But I'm sure your goons
can get it off him.
I mean, he's 15.
Flunking social studies.
So, if you could just
write me a check for
my 10% of half a million,
5 grand,
I'll go out and mingle.
(CHUCKLES)
You mix a hell of
a Caucasian, Jackie.
(ECHOING)
Fifteen-year-old kid.
Is this some sort of a joke?
No. No joke.
No funny stuff, Jackie.
The kid's got it.
Hi, fellas.
Kid just wanted a car.
All the Dude ever wanted
was his rug back.
Not greedy.
It really
tied the room together.
MAN: Darkness washed
over the Dude.
Darker than
a black steer's tokus on
a moonless prairie night.
There was no bottom.
Yeah, yeah, oh, yeah
What condition
my condition was in
I woke up this morning
with the sundown shining in
I found my mind in
a brown paper bag within
I tripped on a cloud
and fell-a eight miles high
I tore my mind on a jagged sky
I just dropped in
To see what condition
my condition was in
Yeah, yeah, oh, yeah
What condition
my condition was in
I pushed my soul
in a deep, dark hole
And then I followed it in
I watched myself crawlin' out
As I was a-crawlin' in
I got up so tight
I couldn't unwind
I saw so much I broke my mind
I just dropped in
To see what condition
my condition was in
Yeah, yeah, oh, yeah
What condition
my condition was in
Someone painted "April Fool"
In big, black letters
on a "Dead End" sign
I had my foot on the gas
as I left the road
And blew out my mind
Eight miles out of Memphis
and I got no spare
Eight miles straight up
downtown somewhere
I just dropped in
To see what condition
my condition was in
I said I just dropped in
To see what condition
my condition was in
Yeah, yeah
O£, yeah
(WHIMPERING)
(SIREN WAILING)
(SINGING)
He was innocent
Not a charge was true
And they say
he ran away branded
(GRUNTING)
Is this your only lD?
I know my rights, man.
You don't know shit, Lebowski.
I want a fucking lawyer,
man.
I want Bill Kunstler, man,
or Ron Kuby.
Mr. Treehorn tells us
that he had to eject you
from his garden party,
that you were drunk
and abusive.
Mr. Treehorn treats objects
like women, man.
Mr. Treehorn draws
a lot of water in this town.
You don't draw shit, Lebowski.
Now, we got a nice quiet
little beach community here,
and I aim to keep it
nice and quiet.
So let me make
something plain.
I don't like you sucking
around bothering our
citizens, Lebowski.
I don't like your
jerk-off name.
jerk-off face.
I don't like your
jerk-off behavior.
And I don't like you,
jerk-off.
Do I make myself clear?
I'm sorry. I wasn't listening.
Ow!
Fucking fascist!
(YELLING)
Stay out of Malibu,
Lebowski.
Stay out of Malibu, deadbeat!
Keep your ugly, fucking,
gold-bricking ass out of
my beach community.
(MUSIC PLAYING ON STEREO)
I want to sleep with you
In the desert tonight
With a billion stars
all around
Jesus, man. Could you
change the channel?
Fuck you, man!
If you don't like
my fucking music,
get your own fucking cab!
I had a really rough...
I'll pull off to the side
and kick your ass out.
Man, come on. I had
a rough night, and I hate
the fucking Eagles, man.
(TIRES SQUEALING)
(HORN HONKING)
Out of my fucking cab! Out!
Man!
Man! Man! Hey!
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING ON RADIO)
(SINGING)
There's a thousand pretty
women waiting out there
And they're all livin'
devil may care
And I'm just the devil
with love to spare
So viva Las Vegas
Viva Las Vegas
Oh, Jesus!
(GRUNTS)
Jeffrey.
Maude?
Love me.
That's my robe.
MAUDE: Tell me about
yourself, Jeffrey.
Well, not much to tell.
I was one of the authors
of the Port Huron Statement.
The original
Port Huron Statement.
Uh-huh.
Not the compromised
second draft.
Then l...
You ever hear of
the Seattle Seven?
That was me.
And there were
six other guys.
And then the music business,
briefly.
Oh?
Yeah.
Roadie for Metallica.
Oh.
Speed of Sound tour.
Mmm-hmm.
Bunch of assholes.
And then, you know,
little of this,
little of that.
My career's slowed down
a little lately.
What do you do
for recreation?
Well, the usual.
Bowl, drive around,
the occasional
acid flashback.
(COUGHING)
MAUDE: What happened
to your house?
Oh, Jackie Treehorn
trashed the place.
He thought I had
your father's money.
He got me out of the way
while he looked for it.
Cocktail?
No, thanks.
It's not my father's money.
It's the foundation's.
Why did he think you have it?
Who does?
Oh, Larry Sellers,
this high school kid.
Real fucking brat.
You know, this is a very
complicated case, Maude.
A lot of ins, a lot of outs.
You know, fortunately,
I'm adhering to a pretty
strict, drug regimen
to keep my mind,
you know, limber,
and I'm very fucking close
to your father's money.
I keep telling you,
it's the foundation's
money.
Father doesn't have any.
What are you talking about?
He's fucking loaded.
No, no. The wealth
is all Mother's.
No, he runs stuff.
We did let him run one
of the companies briefly,
but he didn't do
very well at it.
Oh, he's, you know...
No, he helps administer
the charities now,
and I give him
a reasonable allowance.
He has no money of his own.
I know how he likes
to present himself.
Father's weakness is vanity,
hence the slut.
Do you think he...
What is that, yoga?
It increases the chances
of conception.
(COUGHS)
lncreases...
Well, yes.
What did you think
this was all about?
Fun and games?
I want a child.
Okay, yeah, okay.
But let me... Let me explain
something about the Dude.
Look, Jeffrey,
I don't want a partner.
In fact, I don't want
the father to be someone
I have to see socially
or who will have any interest
in raising the child himself.
Oh. So, that doctor...
Exactly.
Now, what happened
to your face?
Did Jackie Treehorn
do that as well?
No, it was the chief
of police of Malibu,
a real reactionary.
So, your father...
Oh, yeah, I get it.
Yeah. Yeah.
What?
Oh, man.
My thinking about this case
has become very uptight.
Yeah.
Your father.
Jeffrey, what are
you talking about?
Jeffrey!
Walter, if you're there,
pick up the fucking phone,
man.
Come on, Walter.
Pick it up, man.
This is an emergency.
Dude? Dude?
Yeah. Listen, Walter.
I'm at my place. I need
you to come pick me up.
I can't drive, Dude.
It's Erev shabbos.
What?
Erev shabbos.
Erev shabbos. I can't drive.
Man!
I'm not even supposed
to pick up the phone
unless it's an emergency.
This is a fucking emergency!
I understand.
That's why I picked up
the phone.
Walter, you fuck.
We gotta go to Pasadena, man.
Come pick me up or I'm off
the fucking bowling team.
Get out of that
fucking car, man!
Get out of that fucking car!
Get the fuck
out of the car, man.
Get out of the fucking...
Who the fuck
are you, man?
Easy, man!
Relax, man.
No physical harm intended.
Who the fuck are you?
Why you following me
around?
Come on, fuckhead!
Relax, man.
I'm a brother shamus.
Brother Shamus?
Like an Irish monk?
What the fuck are
you talking about?
My name is Da Fino.
I'm a private snoop,
like you, man.
What?
A dick, man.
And let me tell you something,
I dig your work.
Playing one side
against the other,
in bed with everybody.
Fabulous stuff, man.
I'm not...
Fuck it, man.
Just stay away from
my fucking lady friend.
Hey, I'm not messing
with your special lady.
She's not my special lady.
She's my fucking lady friend.
I'm just helping her
conceive, man!
Hey, man. I'm not...
Who are you working for?
Lebowski?
Jackie Treehorn?
The Kneutsons.
Who the fuck are
the Kneutsons?
The Kneutsons,
it's a wandering
daughterjob.
Bunny Lebowski, man.
Her real name
is Fawn Kneutson.
Her parents
want her back, see?
Jesus fucking Christ.
Crazy, huh?
Ran away about a year ago.
The Kneutsons told me
I should show her this
when I found her.
It's the family farm.
It's outside Moorhead,
Minnesota.
They think it'll
make her homesick.
Oh, boy.
How are you gonna keep them
down on the farm
once they've seen
Karl Hungus?
She's been kidnapped,
Da Fino.
Oh, man.
Or I don't know.
Maybe not.
But she's definitely
not around.
Hey, maybe you and me
could pool our resources,
trade information.
(DOG BARKING)
Professional courtesy?
Compeers.
You know what I mean?
Yeah, yeah, I get it.
Fuck off, Da Fino.
And stay away
from my special...
From my fucking
lady friend, man!
The lingonberry pancake.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
Lingonberry pancakes.
Three pigs in blanket.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
DIETER: She has
lingonberry pancakes.
(MEN SPEAKING GERMAN)
I mean, we totally
fucked it up, man.
We fucked up his payoff.
We got the kidnappers
all pissed off.
And Lebowski, you know,
he yelled at me a lot,
but he didn't do
anything, huh?
Well, sometimes
it's a cathartic...
No, no.
I'm saying that
if he knows I'm a fuckup,
why does he leave me
in charge of getting
his wife back?
DUDE: Because he doesn't
fucking want her back, man.
He's had enough.
He no longer digs her.
It's all a show.
Okay, but then
why doesn't he give a shit
about his million bucks?
I mean, he knows we never
handed off his briefcase,
(THUNDER CRASHING)
but he never asked
for it back.
The million bucks
was never in the briefcase.
The briefcase was
fucking empty, man.
The asshole was hoping
that they would kill her.
You threw out a ringer
for a ringer.
Okay, but how does
all this add up to
an emergency?
I'm saying, I see what
you're getting at, Dude.
He kept the money.
My point is...
Here we are, it's shabbos,
the Sabbath,
which I'm allowed to break
only if it's a matter of
life or death.
Will you come off it,
Walter? You're not even
fucking Jewish, man.
What the fuck are
you talking about?
Man, you're fucking
Polish Catholic!
What the fuck
are you talking about?
I converted when
I married Cynthia.
Come on, Dude.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
You know this.
And five fucking years ago,
you were divorced.
So what are you saying?
When you get divorced,
you turn in your library card?
You get a new license?
You stop being Jewish?
This is the driveway.
Jewish as fucking Tevye.
Man.
You know, it's all a part
of your sick Cynthia thing.
Man, taking care of her
fucking dog, going to her
fucking synagogue.
You're living in
the fucking past.
Three thousand years
of beautiful tradition,
from Moses to Sandy Koufax.
You're goddamn right I'm
living in the fucking past!
l've... Jesus.
WALTER:
What the hell happened?
So viva Las Vegas
Viva Las Vegas
(DOG WHINING)
Let's go. Fuck it.
(EXCLAIMS)
DUDE: Where was she, man?
Visiting friends of hers
in Palm Springs.
She just picked up and left,
never bothered to tell us.
Well, I guess
the fucking nihilists
knew where she was.
Jesus, Dude. She never
even kidnapped herself.
Who is this gentleman, Dude?
Who am l?
I'm a fucking veteran.
Come on!
That's who I am.
You shouldn't go
in there, Dude.
He's very angry.
(WHINING)
So, man.
So? She's back,
no thanks to you.
Where's the fucking money,
Lebowski?
A million bucks
from fucking, needy,
little Urban Achievers!
You are scum, man!
Who the hell is he?
Who am l? Who am l?
Walter.
I'm the guy that's gonna
kick your phony,
gold-bricking ass,
that's who I am.
Man.
We know the briefcase
was fucking empty.
We know you kept
the million bucks
for yourself.
You have your story,
I have mine.
I say I entrusted the money
to you and you stole it.
As if we would
ever dream of taking
your bullshit money!
You thought that Bunny
had been kidnapped,
and you were
fucking glad, man.
You could use it as an excuse
to make some money disappear.
All you needed was
a sap to pin it on.
You just met me.
You... You human paraquat.
You figured,
"Oh, here's a loser,
you know, a deadbeat.
"Somebody this square
community won't give
a shit about."
Well, aren't you?
Well, yeah, but...
Get out, both of you.
Look at that fucking phony,
Dude, pretending to be
a fucking millionaire.
Out of this house now,
you bums!
Let me tell you
something else.
I've seen a lot of spinals,
Dude, and this guy's a fake.
A fucking gold-bricker.
Stay away from me, mister!
This guy fucking walks.
I've never been more certain
of anything in my life.
You stay away from me!
Walter, for Christ's sake,
man! He's a cripple.
I said! Get away from me!
Come on. Come on.
(SCREAMING)
Walter, put him down, man!
Yeah, I'll put him down, Dude.
Walk! Achtung, baby!
(GROANS)
(DOG BARKING)
(SOBBING)
(PANTING)
Come on, man. Help me
put him back in his chair.
WALTER: At least
they had the fucking
decency to tell us
that we were fighting
the communists.
Whereas this
whole fucking thing,
this whole fucking thing
is nothing about nothing,
about oil,
which is what I personally
hear, Dude.
Sure you'll see
some tank battles,
but fighting in desert
is very different from
fighting in canopy jungle.
I mean, Nam was
a foot soldier's war,
whereas this thing should...
You know, should be
a piece of cake.
I mean, I had an M16, Jacko,
not an Abrams fucking tank.
Me and Charlie,
eyeball to eyeball.
Yeah.
That's fucking combat.
The man in the black
pajamas, Dude.
Worthy fucking adversary.
Who's in pajamas, Walter?
Shut the fuck up, Donny.
Whereas what we have here,
a bunch of fig eaters
wearing towels
on their head,
trying to find reverse
on a Soviet tank.
This is not a worthy
fucking adversary.
QUINTANA: Hey!
What's this
day-of-rest shit?
What's this bullshit?
I don't fucking care!
It don't matter to Jesus.
But you not fooling me,
man.
You might fool the fucks
in the league office
but you don't fool Jesus.
It's Bush league
psych-out stuff.
Laughable, man!
I would've fucked you
in the ass Saturday.
I'll fuck you in the ass
next Wednesday instead.
(WHOOPS)
You got a date
Wednesday, baby!
He's cracking.
...the whole concept of age.
I mean, many learned men
have disputed this
but in the 14th century,
the Rambam...
Well, they finally
did it.
They killed
my fucking car.
We want the money,
Lebowski.
Ja. Otherwise,
we kill the girl.
Ja. It seems you have
forgotten our little deal,
Lebowski.
You don't have the
fucking girl, dipshit.
We know you never did.
Are these the Nazis,
Walter?
No, Donny.
These men are nihilists.
There's nothing
to be afraid of.
We don't care.
We still want the money,
Lebowski, or we fuck you up.
Fuck you.
Fuck the three of you.
Cool it, Walter.
No. Without a hostage,
there is no ransom.
That's what ransom is.
Those are the fucking rules.
His girlfriend
gave up her toe.
She thought we could
get $1 million.
It's not fair.
Fair?
Who's the fucking nihilists
around here, you bunch
of fucking crybabies?
Cool it, Walter.
Hey, look, pal.
DUDE: There never
was any money.
The big Lebowski gave me
an empty briefcase,
so take it up with him, man.
And I would like
my undies back.
Are these guys gonna
hurt us, Walter?
No, Donny.
These men are cowards.
Okay!
So we takes the money
you have on you, and
we calls it even.
Fuck you.
Hey, no. Come on, Walter.
Come on, we're ending
this thing cheap, man.
No. What's mine is mine.
No, come on, Walter.
No funny stuff.
All right. All right.
I got 4 bucks, almost 5.
I got $1·.
WALTER: What's mine is mine.
We fuck you up, man!
We takes the money!
Come and get it.
We fuck you up!
Show me what you got,
nihilists.
I fuck you!
Walter, come on.
He's got a sword.
Fucking dipshit with
a nine-toed woman!
I fuck you! Fuck you!
I fuck you!
(EXCLAIMING)
(GRUNTING)
Take it easy, man.
I fuck you!
Take the $4.
(GRUNTING)
I fuck you!
I'm gonna hit you with
the fucking ball, man.
(SCREAMING)
(SPITS)
MAN: Hey, dickhead!
Anti-Semite.
I fuck you in the ass!
I fuck you! I fuck you!
We got a man down, Dude!
(GROANING)
Oh, God. They shot him, man.
He's not shot. No, Dude.
Are you shot, Donny?
There weren't
any shots fired.
Huh?
It's a heart attack.
Call the medics, Dude.
I'd go myself,
but I'm pumping blood,
might pass out.
Rest easy, good buddy.
You're doing fine.
We got help choppering in.
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
Hello, gentlemen.
You are the bereaved?
Yeah, man.
Francis Donnelly,
pleased to meet you.
Jeff Lebowski.
Walter Sobchak.
The Dude actually is...
Excuse me?
Oh, nothing.
Yes. I understand
you're taking away
the remains?
Yeah.
We have the urn.
I assume this is credit card?
Yeah.
(CLEARS THROAT)
What's this?
Now, that's for the urn.
Don't need it.
We're scattering the ashes.
Yes. So we were informed.
However, we must, of course,
transmit the remains to you
in a receptacle.
That's $1·0.
It is our most modestly
priced receptacle.
Well, can't we just...
$1·0?
They range up to $3,000.
We're...
Can't we just rent it
from you, you know?
Sir, this is a mortuary
not a rental house.
We're scattering
the fucking ashes!
Walter, Walter.
Just because we're bereaved
doesn't make us saps.
Sir, please lower
your voices.
Man, don't you have,
you know, something else
we can put him in?
You know?
That is our most modestly
priced receptacle.
God damn it!
Is there a Ralph's
around here?
(SEAGULLS SQUAWKING)
Donny was a good bowler
and a good man.
He was one of us.
He was a man who loved
the outdoors and bowling.
And as a surfer
he explored the beaches
of Southern California
from La Jolla to Leo Carrillo
and up to Pismo.
He died...
He died as so many young men
of his generation,
before his time.
In your wisdom, Lord,
you took him,
as you took so many bright,
flowering young men
at Khe Sanh, at Lan Doc,
at Hill 364.
These young men
gave their lives,
and so did Donny.
Donny, who loved bowling.
And so,
Theodore Donald Kerabatsos,
in accordance with
what we think your dying
wishes might well have been,
we commit your final
mortal remains
to the bosom of
the Pacific Ocean
which you loved so well.
Good night, sweet prince.
(lNHALES)
Shit.
Oh, shit, Dude. I'm sorry.
Goddamn wind.
Fuck, god damn it, Walter!
You fucking asshole!
Shit, Dude. I'm sorry.
Everything's a fucking
travesty with you, man!
I'm sorry.
It was an accident.
What was that shit
about Vietnam?
Dude, I'm sorry.
What the fuck does anything
have to do with Vietnam?
Dude, I'm sorry.
What the fuck are
you talking about?
Dude, I'm sorry.
Fucking...
Fuck, Walter.
Come on, Dude.
Hey, fuck it, man.
Let's go bowling.
And when you're sittin' there
In your silk upholstered chair
Talkin' to some rich folks
that you know
Well, I hope you don't see me
In my ragged company
O£, but you know
I could never be alone
Two oat sodas, Gary.
Right. Good luck tomorrow.
Yeah, thanks, man.
I was sorry
to hear about Donny.
Oh, yeah. Well, you know,
sometimes you eat the bear,
and sometimes, you know...
Hey, man.
How do you do, Dude?
I wondered if
I'd see you again.
I wouldn't miss
the semis.
Oh, yeah?
How's things been going?
Well, you know,
strikes and gutters,
ups and downs.
Sure. I got you.
Yeah.
Thanks, Gary.
Well, take care, man.
Gotta get back.
Sure. Take it easy, Dude.
Oh, yeah.
I know that you will.
Yeah. Well,
the Dude abides.
Walter.
The Dude abides.
I don't know about you,
but I take comfort in that.
It's good knowing
he's out there,
the Dude, taking her easy
for all us sinners.
I sure hope
he makes the finals.
Well, that about does her.
Wraps her all up.
Things seem to have
worked out pretty good
for the Dude and Walter.
And it was
a pretty good story,
don't you think?
Made me laugh
to beat the band.
Parts anyway.
I didn't like seeing Donny go.
But then I happen to know
that there's a little
Lebowski on the way.
I guess that's the way
the whole darned
human comedy keeps
perpetuating itself
down through the generations.
Westward the wagons,
across the sands of time
until we...
Oh, look at me.
I'm rambling again.
Well, I hope you folks
enjoyed yourselves.
Catch you later on
down the trail.
Say, friend, you got any more
of that good sarsaparilla?
Take me down, little Susie
Take me down
I know you think
you're the queen
Of the underground
Send me dead flowers
every morning
by the mail
Send me dead flowers
to my wedding
And I won't forget to put
roses on your grave
No, I won't forget
to put roses
On your grave
(POP MUSIC PLAYING)
Bright light city
gonna set my soul
Gonna set my soul on fire
Got a whole lot of money
that's ready to burn
So get those stakes up higher
There's a thousand pretty
women livin' out there
They're all livin'
devil may care
And I'm just a devil
with love to spare
So viva Las Vegas
Viva Las Vegas
with your neon flashing
And your one-arm
bandits crashing
All those hopes down the drain
Viva Las Vegas turnin'
day into nighttime
Night into daytime
If you see it once
You'll never be the same again
I'm gonna keep on
keep on runnin'
If it costs me
my very last dime
If I wind up broke
Well, I'll always remember
That I had a swingin' time
I'm gonna give it
everything I've got
Lady Luck, please
let the dice stay hot
£et me shoot a seven
on every shot
So viva Las Vegas
Viva Las Vegas
Viva
£as Vegas